<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuance of Albions England: by the first author. VV.VV.</title>
            <title>Albions England. Book 14-16</title>
            <author>Warner, William, 1558?-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14784</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854810</idno>
  <idno type="VID">20257</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240934117</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 25085</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S119603</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99854810e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20257)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1045:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuance of Albions England: by the first author. VV.VV.</title>
                  <title>Albions England. Book 14-16</title>
                  <author>Warner, William, 1558?-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 337-416 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kyngston [and Richard Bradock?] for George Potter, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Warner.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Contains books 14-16.</note>
                  <note>Richard Bradock may have printed quire B (STC).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.j.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:1"/>
            <p>A CONTI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVANCE OF ALBIONS ENG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LAND:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the first Author.</hi> W. W.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>PARNASSO ET APOLLINE DIGNA</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Felix Kingston</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Felix Kyngston</hi> for <hi>George Potter,</hi> and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Bible. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR EDVVARD COKE, KNIGHT, Lord Chief-Iustice of his Maiesties <hi>Court of Common-Pleas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat <hi>Caesars</hi> haue lesse <hi>Poems</hi> grac't,</l>
               <l>Lesse in Sublimitie this plac't,</l>
               <l>(Vnworthie though your Deapth, I graunt,</l>
               <l>Yet might Ours past great Patrons vaunt)</l>
               <l>Wooes your Allowance, whom my <hi>Muse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth its select <hi>Mecaenas</hi> chuse.</l>
               <l>If with the right-hand what I giue</l>
               <l>Be taken with the left, should grieue</l>
               <l>So much more lesse by how much more</l>
               <l>This meant I orphanag'd before:</l>
               <l>Which now to you, as destinate,</l>
               <l>I, yours deuoted, dedicate:</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Most humbly, <hi>William Warner.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y diuers importun'd to this,</l>
               <l>I send it foorth, such as it is.</l>
               <l>This idle Arte that lets it thriue</l>
               <l>Was Midwife to the Abortiue:</l>
               <l>Doe dandle, knock it on the head,</l>
               <l>All one to me aliue or dead.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Musists,</hi> though themselues they please,</l>
               <l>Their Dotage els finds Meede nor Ease:</l>
               <l>Vouch't <hi>Spencer</hi> in that Ranke preferd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Per Accidens,</hi> only interr'd</l>
               <l>Nigh Venerable <hi>Chaucer,</hi> lost,</l>
               <l>Had not kinde <hi>Brigham</hi> reard him Cost,</l>
               <l>Found next the doore Church-outed neere,</l>
               <l>And yet a Knight, Arch-<hi>Lauriat</hi> Heere.</l>
               <l>Adde <hi>Stows</hi> late antiquarious Pen,</l>
               <l>That annald for vngratefull Men:</l>
               <l>Next Chronicler omit it not,</l>
               <l>His licenc't Basons little got:</l>
               <l>Liu'd poorely where he Trophies gaue,</l>
               <l>Lies poorely There in notelesse graue.</l>
               <l>As These in Theirs, so we in Ours,</l>
               <l>And who write best lose better houres,</l>
               <l>And most what but for Nods doe cense</l>
               <l>Saints, senselesse of more Recompence.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20257:4"/>
               <l> No maruell, Poëtrie seemes gon</l>
               <l>To <hi>Bedlam</hi> now from <hi>Helicon.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yea most her Priests Intemperature</l>
               <l>So diffreth from their Literature,</l>
               <l>Their Literature obscenously</l>
               <l>So suteth to Scurrilitie,</l>
               <l>As if, <hi>Aonides,</hi> it hold,</l>
               <l>You from your sacred Hill of old</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pierides</hi> will dare to skold.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mnemosynes,</hi> retract I this,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ambrosia</hi> sweete and <hi>Nectar</hi> is</l>
               <l>Your food, and yee eterniz'd liue,</l>
               <l>Not as yee take, but as yee giue.</l>
               <l>Inuested with Imperiall Robe,</l>
               <l>Or circumfer'd the varied Globe,</l>
               <l>Arts, Armes, or what, for what, or who,</l>
               <l>Out-liues one Age vnles by you?</l>
               <l>For <hi>Homer,</hi> at <hi>Achillis</hi> Tombe,</l>
               <l>This blist did <hi>Alexander</hi> doome.</l>
               <l>In Mysteries oft as in those</l>
               <l>Ilias, Trans-shapes, Aeneidos,</l>
               <l>In patent Letter also ye</l>
               <l>Make longest dead aliue to be.</l>
               <l>Thrice-noble Thrice Three <hi>Ioues</hi> high Breede▪</l>
               <l>How happie ye whom happiest neede?</l>
               <l>Nor sleepeth your <hi>Anagraphie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The sensuall Follies of the Hie,</l>
               <l>Nor crested Chorles that for Coynes skill,</l>
               <l>More Standings heare than Bellies fill,</l>
               <l>Nor those could wish ye them passe-by</l>
               <l>As if a dungled Asse should die.</l>
               <l>Yet he that fierd th' <hi>Ephesian</hi> Phane</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20257:4"/>
               <l> Did it your Pens Report to gaine:</l>
               <l>As <hi>Faux,</hi> that him might scorne Compeere</l>
               <l>For Proiect more prodigious heere.</l>
               <l>Thus vertuous and prophane, in few,</l>
               <l>Haue Perpetuitie from you,</l>
               <l>Praisd or dispraisd examplarlie,</l>
               <l>So profiting Posteritie.</l>
               <l>Sixe passed Presses past vs ill,</l>
               <l>As, not vnlikely, this Presse will.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muse,</hi> that twi-bucketted hast bin,</l>
               <l>Emptedst poore wit poore winde to win,</l>
               <l>Twice towredst to a seuerall Steeple,</l>
               <l>Didst kenne no Patrons but the People,</l>
               <l>Shunne Eares vnarted, rude, precise,</l>
               <l>Seeke Loues that ours shall sympathize.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Theirs <hi>W. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:5"/>
            <head>A Table for euery of the seuerall Bookes, to find out the speciall Stories and matters, <hi>directing from their Chapters.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>The fourteenth Booke.</head>
               <item>A <hi>Parabola,</hi> or comparatiue Relation from the <hi>English-</hi>Raignes since the Conquest, to the late Raigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Chap. 80.</item>
               <item>More tending to the like Argument, &amp;c. Chap. 81.</item>
               <item>Her Life, Vertues, Death, Detractors, into Particulars epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: And of the letter. P. Chap. 82.</item>
               <item>An Entrance into the Historie of the <hi>Picts,</hi> somtimes a martiall Nation here: Of <hi>Scotlands</hi> fatall Chaire, and of certaine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Predictions here lately effected. Chap. 83.</item>
               <item>Of the first <hi>Scotch-</hi>King in this Isle: The first Armies betweene them and the <hi>Picts:</hi> Their appeasement, And a Slaughter of the <hi>Britaines.</hi> Chap. 84.</item>
               <item>Warres betweene the <hi>Picts</hi> and the <hi>Scots:</hi> How the <hi>Britaines</hi> dealt aduantagiously against Either People: The <hi>Romanes</hi> successe Here, and of the <hi>Picts</hi> their Prowesse. Chap. 85.</item>
               <item>How the <hi>Picts</hi> debelled the <hi>Scots:</hi> Of Queene <hi>Cartandis:</hi> More of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and of the King of <hi>Penthlands</hi> death. Chap. 86</item>
               <item>How the <hi>Scots</hi> recouered their Countrie: They and the <hi>Picts</hi> chased the <hi>Romanes:</hi> Subdued and inthralled the <hi>Britaines,</hi> And of the <hi>Britaines</hi> then Sloth and Effeminacie. Chap. 87</item>
               <item>How the <hi>Britaines</hi> subiected themselues to the <hi>Armoricans</hi> or <hi>French-Brutaines:</hi> Of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and more of the warlike <hi>Picts.</hi> Chap. 88</item>
               <item>A Tale of a faire yong Nunne and an old Pandresse. Chap. 89</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20257:5"/>
               <item>Of the long continued League and Confedracie betweene the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> against the <hi>English:</hi> Impacable warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Picts</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> and of an Elusion fatall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Picts.</hi> Chap. 90</item>
               <item>A Tale of <hi>Robin-goodfellow.</hi> Chap. 91</item>
               <item>Of the mercilesse End of the Martiall King and kingdome of the <hi>Picts.</hi> Chap. 92</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The fifteenth Booke.</head>
               <item>OF the Propagators of vs moderne <hi>English:</hi> An Entrance into the Historie of <hi>Wales,</hi> &amp;c. Chap. 93</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Makbeth</hi> the Tyrant: Of the noble <hi>Scot Fleance:</hi> The pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage of loue betweene him and the Kings Daughter of <hi>Wales,</hi> and of their royall Posteritie. Chap. 94</item>
               <item>Of the most barbarous and vnexampled preuented Massacre, plotted against the whole Parliament and State of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> 1605. &amp;c. Chap. 95</item>
               <item>A few Cautions for Papists: Their senselesse Seduction: Popes, Papisme, and their trecherous Policies in part described. Chap. 96</item>
               <item>Of S. <hi>Austin</hi> and the Clerkes of <hi>Bangor.</hi> Chap. 97</item>
               <item>Of moderne Hypocrites, &amp; schismaticall Singularitie. Chap. 98</item>
               <item>A Merriment of a saintish vnsanctified Hostesse, &amp;c. Chap. 99</item>
               <item>A speaking Vision, set downe in the person of good Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Chap. 100</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The sixteenth Booke.</head>
               <item>HOw the Principalitie of South<hi>-Wales</hi> and the Lordship of <hi>Glamorgan</hi> were subdued to <hi>England:</hi> Of <hi>Iestin</hi> his faire Daughter: The vanitie of curious Ornaments and arted Beautie. Chap. 101</item>
               <item>A merrie Iest, by occasion of a Perwig: Of Pride: Our vaine Progresse throughout this life: Of the Intemperance and Amisses in some Iusticers. Chap. 102</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:20257:6"/>
               <item>A plaine Loue-letter, from a countrie Bachelor to <hi>Iestins</hi> faire Daughter. Chap. 103</item>
               <item>Her opinion of honest Plainnesse, Opposition to Pride and Flatterie, Approbation of the meane-Estate, and Resolution for her Louer. Chap. 104</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Nest,</hi> Lady of <hi>Brechnock,</hi> her dishonorable Reuenge against her owne Sonne, &amp;c. Chap. 105</item>
               <item>Of <hi>William de Bruse</hi> his inhumane Crueltie. Chap. 106</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Wales</hi> intirely subiected to <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. A Monarchall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerture of <hi>Brute</hi> his Diuident, &amp;c. Chap. 107</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="14" type="book">
            <pb n="337" facs="tcp:20257:6"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTEENTH BOOKE OF <hi>ALBIONS ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="80" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. LXXX.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ET Is the soueraigne Sonne did shine when paperd laste our penne,</l>
                  <l>Yet still alike the Lighte, so God makes Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorites of men.</l>
                  <l>And hee eternall bids that wee our terren Gods obay,</l>
                  <l>As Ours shall we, though should to vs his Edict other say,</l>
                  <l>Than that we sing our <hi>England</hi> now in <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane,</hi> howbeit,</l>
                  <l>Not suddenly we can, perhaps, innatiue Termes forgitte.</l>
                  <l>Nor shall, nor shoulde yt aught distaste that <hi>England</hi> alters name,</l>
                  <l>Sith it nor Yts laste Mistresse can by aught be outed fame.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Britane</hi> as a nouell Name to <hi>England</hi> we admitte,</l>
                  <l>Sith frequent and authentick be Aucthorities for it.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Albion</hi> to haue been, or but a Fiction we dispute:</l>
                  <l>But, if no Fiction, <hi>Albion</hi> then is Senior vnto <hi>Brute.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, that this Latter was haue been for Names-skill, would confute,</l>
                  <l>When in that primer Race of Kings in name the Sixth did sute.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Albions England,</hi> our poore Lynes, be <hi>Britanes England</hi> now,</l>
                  <l>Or eyther, nayther, or what-else: Okes breake when reeds but bowe.</l>
                  <l>But who takes notice of a Toy, the Title or our Booke?</l>
                  <pb n="338" facs="tcp:20257:7"/>
                  <l> Or how should Either preiudice though curiously mistook?</l>
                  <l>Auspiciously then, <hi>Muse</hi> go on, remembring by the way</l>
                  <l>Our late interred Mistresse, and of all our Masters say</l>
                  <l>Their varied Reignes, so Hers from Theirs the better to purtraie.</l>
                  <l>Yea speake, and speake aduisedly, Those that in Thes be read,</l>
                  <l>(Not <hi>Romists,</hi> nather Humors in Preiudicacie lead)</l>
                  <l>Whose in this Catalogue of Reignes compeered hers last dead.</l>
                  <l>All heere was then contraryed when the <hi>Conqueror</hi> was King,</l>
                  <l>and oft his vassalde English he gainst forraine Swords did bring</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rufus,</hi> that for excessiue Chase vnpeopled many a towne,</l>
                  <l>And perisht in that sporte, was not of few malign'd his Crowne.</l>
                  <l>Like deare to <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> first <hi>Henry</hi> voyded not</l>
                  <l>That Auarice and Rigor to his Virtues were a blot.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Stephens</hi> first Intrution to the poynt of his decease</l>
                  <l>No tongue was lesse familier heere then was the tonge of Peace.</l>
                  <l>For Empery more puissant than was second <hi>Henry</hi> none;</l>
                  <l>Yeat his Ambitious prelats, Queene, and sons disturbd that Throne.</l>
                  <l>The valerous <hi>Cor-de-lion</hi> by his warres and ransome so</l>
                  <l>Exhausted Treasure, as no more, but Gods, could men forgoe.</l>
                  <l>Saue that the better worser spead, <hi>Iohns</hi> raigne mighte be compar'd,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Michaels</hi> and the Dragons fight, so Crowne and Miter squarde</l>
                  <l>What with a <hi>French-</hi>imbulled-Kinge, and Barrons often broyls,</l>
                  <l>Third <hi>Henryes</hi> thence prouoked war that publique-weale turmoyles</l>
                  <l>The <hi>French, Welsh, Scots,</hi> becaus their skorge, yll brook't first <hi>Edwards</hi> glory,</l>
                  <l>Nor welcō'd we a ceaselesse war, though full of worth his story.</l>
                  <l>Yf what was second <hi>Edwards</hi> Rule be askt, is aun'swerd thus,</l>
                  <l>So turbulent as may be wisht that neuer such rule vs,</l>
                  <l>Third <hi>Edward</hi> was armipotent, his Subiects nerethelesse</l>
                  <l>him murmuringly did tax that them taxes did oppresse.</l>
                  <l>The second <hi>Richard</hi> ouerkind to Parasits, and foe</l>
                  <l>to aunchant Cronets, feweld all might fier to <hi>Englands</hi> woe.</l>
                  <l>But his Erectment hardly did fourth <hi>Henry</hi> pleade vnto:</l>
                  <l>and that he gainde the Cause at length, loue more then law did doe:</l>
                  <pb n="339" facs="tcp:20257:7"/>
                  <l> Whether fifte <hi>Henryes</hi> costly warres, or death (he so belou'd)</l>
                  <l>More touched His ingrudge or greefe, a question may be mou'd.</l>
                  <l>Sixt <hi>Henry,</hi> rare for Sanctity, more fit for Cowle than Crowne,</l>
                  <l>and ouerruled in his rule, much pittied, was put downe.</l>
                  <l>Fourth <hi>Edward</hi> in reuerted raigne to <hi>Yorkests</hi> found small reste,</l>
                  <l>Or England foyzon: Kings contend and Comons be opprest.</l>
                  <l>His Infant sonne <hi>Edward</hi> the fift, vncrowned not vncroste,</l>
                  <l>Mou'd cōmon tears when for his Crown both Crown &amp; life he loste,</l>
                  <l>The Regi-cids, third <hi>Richards</hi> reigne, was tragick vnto all,</l>
                  <l>And lastly to himself▪ for so to ryse is so to fall.</l>
                  <l>Seauenth <hi>Henry,</hi> the Vnitor of those Flowers that long dissented,</l>
                  <l>Of his Retriuers Prooling<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much (as well he might) repented.</l>
                  <l>Eight <hi>Henry,</hi> though victorious and triumphant, was not quitt</l>
                  <l>of mvrmerd Axes: Recluses vn-cloystred grudged yt.</l>
                  <l>Sixt <hi>Edward,</hi> of most pregnant witte and virtues, <hi>Englands</hi> hope,</l>
                  <l>Too young to stint his Princes stryfes vext, not vnvext, the Pope.</l>
                  <l>Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> nature good, abus'd by <hi>Romes</hi> seducing Crew,</l>
                  <l>might haue allowance, saue for blood from Saints her Butchers drew.</l>
                  <l>How also from the Fourth to the Eight of <hi>Henryes</hi> did ensue</l>
                  <l>A long deuouring ciuill warre, is History too trew.</l>
                  <l>But we haue seene such peacefull warre, such warlike peace, and all</l>
                  <l>So blest in prosperous Policie as Times admire it shall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:20257:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 81.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OR be it vnderstood not all fore-cited faulted much,</l>
                  <l>But were for most renowned Kings, though Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects greefes we touch.</l>
                  <l>Obserue we rather, euer since that <hi>Phocas</hi> prouded <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With that big Title, <hi>supreame Sea,</hi> most Chronicles doe doome.</l>
                  <l>(The workes for most of Friars and Monkes) all Princes bad or good,</l>
                  <l>Not as they were, but as against or with her Pomp, they stood.</l>
                  <l>Hence trecherous Vassales, Kings owne Sonnes, rebelling by her Bull,</l>
                  <l>Whilst Princes good seem'd penn-Forelorns fild <hi>Romes Pantheon</hi> full.</l>
                  <l>Then rather sportiue be her pennes than powrefull to depraue,</l>
                  <l>Where willfull error blindeth not. But leauing <hi>Rome</hi> to raue,</l>
                  <l>this <hi>Normaine</hi> race of Kings we taxe of Publique-weale offended</l>
                  <l>for harshar Priuates than may be gainst her deceaste intended:</l>
                  <l>Though all that royall Streene had much wherein to be commended:</l>
                  <l>May there succeeding Off-springs such euen with the Sunne be ended.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> compared yeat with Theis whence she descended,</l>
                  <l>Not them among a Paritie is fully apprehended:</l>
                  <l>For this heauen-rapted Lady best may Reignes <hi>Idea</hi> boste:</l>
                  <l>and yee that faste for better faer may kisse, perhaps, the poste.</l>
                  <l>O Stomacks cloyd with dainties, Churles amids Aboundance poore,</l>
                  <l>Be your Phisition Pilles, and Wante Remembrancer of Stoore.</l>
                  <l>Had not the same (an other-Same) succeeded that succeeds,</l>
                  <l>Yee lesse had wrong'd the Phaenix dead, and more approu'd her deeds.</l>
                  <l>Nor meruell we that Popelings her nor Puritanes should brook,</l>
                  <l>The present Maiestie from Such like censuring must looke.</l>
                  <pb n="341" facs="tcp:20257:8"/>
                  <l> Nay, euen for very Nouelties that Vulgres doe affect,</l>
                  <l>the best continued Gouernment as tedious they reiect,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Grecians, Romanes,</hi> euery Realms digests, obseruing this,</l>
                  <l>Extenuates the wonder: Then a greate wonder is,</l>
                  <l>That when so many learned Clarks and others shee did rayse,</l>
                  <l>Or for a <hi>Metaphysick</hi> hold the Proiect of her prayse,</l>
                  <l>or slothfully be scilent, or for weeping cannot write,</l>
                  <l>or think from gratefull Offices her Toombe should them acquite,</l>
                  <l>Or (likelier) tract of Lucre, which doth such a sent prefer,</l>
                  <l>As in that present pleasante Chase they are at losse of her,</l>
                  <l>That we touch first the Shoore wherto their statelier ships shold fare,</l>
                  <l>which ydlie ride at anchor, whilst what we shall doe we dare,</l>
                  <l>That is, at farthest but to haue of her a kenning, and</l>
                  <l>Let Pilots expedite the rest that better knowe to lande.</l>
                  <l>First though suppose an <hi>Elegie</hi> the proheme of my Muse,</l>
                  <l>For her, whome shoulde we also blanch we also should abuse.</l>
                  <l>Then let vs rather faulte to Art than Office, sith we owe</l>
                  <l>To her heroick virtues more then how to pay we knowe,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of Expeditions, Vioges, Ayds vnto forreyn States,</l>
                  <l>Tryumphant Victories, Escapes from many trecherous bates,</l>
                  <l>Commenced in her Raigne in fewe we formerly did touch,</l>
                  <l>her in-bred Vertues howbeit clame betterd Muse by much.</l>
                  <l>Liue euer though, not for th'art myne, my Muse (no Muse, god wot)</l>
                  <l>But in this Forehead of our Songe by Please-times now forgott.</l>
                  <l>For those great Artists that did her aliue euen deifie,</l>
                  <l>Now to her sowle-vnbodied doe meere Temporizers dye.</l>
                  <l>When none so resteth glorefide by selfe-Achiuements, as</l>
                  <l>By fame-retriued Digests that from lauriett Pennes doe pas.</l>
                  <l>She blessed one, vnblissed now, re-blissed might he liue,</l>
                  <l>If that a Legend of her life he to the world shall giue.</l>
                  <l>Expecting which, some pen-past Tracts of ours in Theame so deepe</l>
                  <l>Shall to the compleate Science of that wowed Author sleepe:</l>
                  <l>Sufficeth her into her lawdes we through A Cranny peepe.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="chapter">
               <pb n="342" facs="tcp:20257:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 82.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>LIZABETH</hi> (Euen Heer me thinks, repeating but thy name</l>
                  <l>Illustrious turne our lynes, thy selfe sufficing to thy fame)</l>
                  <l>That sleepest sweetly to thy selfe that so to vs did'st wake,</l>
                  <l>From vs in letters leaste, not laste in loue, these Nombres take.</l>
                  <l>to be suspect to adulate (although our eares haue heard</l>
                  <l>vngratefull tongues) of feare no cause, for truth will bee preferd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From long imprisonment, and still expectance to haue dyde</l>
                  <l>Of papalle Furie, God, on whome she euermore relyde:</l>
                  <l>Maugre her Foes (not then a few, for scarce a Prince beside</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Rome</hi> not either awed, or could other Loore abide)</l>
                  <l>possessed her of <hi>Englands</hi> Throne, vs of the Gospells lighte,</l>
                  <l>By her with constant zeale vphild gainst Schismes and potent spight.</l>
                  <l>A princesse fayre in flower of youth to heauen-wards more deuoted,</l>
                  <l>Or one in all that Earth affoords aboundantler that flooted,</l>
                  <l>Yeat lesser vpon wordly Pompe, Maiestick though, that dooted,</l>
                  <l>And dying old a Virgin, times by-passed none haue noted,</l>
                  <l>The mighty King of <hi>Sweuen</hi> sewd to wedde her for his Queene.</l>
                  <l>Braue Troupes with <hi>Valoies</hi> heire of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> heer for the like were seen.</l>
                  <l>The Archduke too of <hi>Austrich,</hi> and greate Potentates a many</l>
                  <l>much laboured her Marrage, not obtayned though of any.</l>
                  <l>Howbeit affablitie and intertainmentes sweete,</l>
                  <l>Mixt with admired Maiesty, in her did ioyntly meete.</l>
                  <l>None better aunswerd Ambasies in whatsoeuer tongue:</l>
                  <l>Effected more in Christndome, yea, Infidelles among:</l>
                  <pb n="343" facs="tcp:20257:9"/>
                  <l> Our either <hi>Achademyes</hi> heard her learning much expresse:</l>
                  <l>No Lady Could more Courtshipp, or well-nigardiz'd yt lesse,</l>
                  <l>For Musick, portly Gate, and daunce did more applause possesse:</l>
                  <l>More louing to her subiects, and from them more loue did winne:</l>
                  <l>Rewarded more well-doings, and was greeued more at sinne:</l>
                  <l>Had causes more of Rygor, yeat more mercifull there in:</l>
                  <l>Preserued more of the publique Peace, our Realme becomming so</l>
                  <l>Even <hi>Achelous</hi> horne to vs <hi>Palladium</hi> gainst the Foe.</l>
                  <l>Her Bountie ofte innabled gainst their Foos themselues to quitte,</l>
                  <l>Distressed Kings and States, the Law of Nations praysing yt:</l>
                  <l>Whence Forrens did our Labours, whilst at home in peace we sitt.</l>
                  <l>She and her Senators vnlike those Citizens that so</l>
                  <l>Once doored on their Treasure that, subdewed by the foe,</l>
                  <l>And lockt into their Treasury, hee doom'd them starue or feede</l>
                  <l>Vppon theyr goulde, which, yf ymploy'd, had helpt them in their need</l>
                  <l>Nor lesse her prayse in this (And may all Princes like obserue)</l>
                  <l>She choose a Coūsell wise, and not from theyr Designes would swerue</l>
                  <l>And whoso greate whom she not awde, what Fauorite spard shee,</l>
                  <l>Yf dangerous to the State. Not aught in rashnesse would decree.</l>
                  <l>Her Temperance, rare virtues and heroyck parts were such</l>
                  <l>As perfect <hi>Panegyricks</hi> heere should but defect too much.</l>
                  <l>More blessed year, her Sowle, that should no longer heere soiourne</l>
                  <l>Did vnto God, from whome yt cam, in Sanctitie retourne.</l>
                  <l>The passed, present, following Dayes were gloomy, Aier, yea marble</l>
                  <l>And trūkes of trees seem'd then to weep, no birds were heard to warbl</l>
                  <l>Beasts silent, that with Rationales was all a-mort suppose,</l>
                  <l>When heauen resum'd her soule, and earth it <hi>Paragon</hi> should loose.</l>
                  <l>Rest may that better parte of thine with God, and it in graue</l>
                  <l>In sweet security, till both vnited glory haue.</l>
                  <l>And should Succession fault in not remunerating thee</l>
                  <l>With such a Monument, as is both wish't and hop't shall be,</l>
                  <l>Thy long and glorious Scepter and innatiue Virtues shall</l>
                  <l>Eternize Trophies to thy Ghoste, and checke Detractors all.</l>
                  <pb n="344" facs="tcp:20257:10"/>
                  <l> Of which are some would States-men seeme, but Parasits more sure,</l>
                  <l>(and such, no doubt, respected where they would their hopes immure)</l>
                  <l>Doe from the Pollicy of those her dayes, and from that State</l>
                  <l>whereby and wherin she did rule and leaue this Realme of late</l>
                  <l>so derrogate, as if death sick, and meanes exhaust for better,</l>
                  <l>had <hi>England</hi> languisht, only to this Change for health a debter.</l>
                  <l>What Pollicie precelled though it she preceded in?</l>
                  <l>Or can to Her succeeded be Precellant? who hath byn?</l>
                  <l>vngratefull, or forgitfull men, or Apes to Innouation,</l>
                  <l>Though with a prudent King indeede be eik't an ancient Nation,</l>
                  <l>Knowe our Weale-publiques blisse is now a parale'lld Creation,</l>
                  <l>wherein Religion and our Lawes persever in their Station,</l>
                  <l>Yea blisse vs doth the Simpathy of <hi>Nows</hi> to <hi>Thens</hi> Relation.</l>
                  <l>For when the Sun that now is sett in our Horizon shin'd,</l>
                  <l>Yt gaue a lefte completion to our Weale in euery Kind.</l>
                  <l>to hers like Raygne, saue his that raignes, more wisht is than deuin'd:</l>
                  <l>A Phoenix for a Phoenix t'ys in his Suns-rise we finde.</l>
                  <l>More to theyr proper Elements inaugurated none,</l>
                  <l>Than shee to hers by-passed, he to his possessed Throne.</l>
                  <l>And may his practis'd Royalty, and royall precepts frame</l>
                  <l>His Issue to like issue, and we pray and hope the same:</l>
                  <l>And may those tongues fall-fowle that her interred shall defame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What Princes though but some, at least for others faults, wil blame thē</l>
                  <l>faults which wold Parlaments could cleanse as can a letter name thē.</l>
                  <l>For of our Alphabet the. P. doth omenously begin</l>
                  <l>Of these this much distasted Ranck, She taxt perhaps therin,</l>
                  <l>Though vse-full euery one, and none, by her abuse a sinne:</l>
                  <l>As Proctors, Puruiors, Purseuants, Post-stagres, Peter-men,</l>
                  <l>Promotors, Paritors, and, as offensiue now and then,</l>
                  <l>Two for their Functions reuerent Pees. Besides which three-times three,</l>
                  <l>Papists and giddy Puritanes, were other Rankes not free</l>
                  <l>Of Publique-weales <hi>Antipathie,</hi> prooling and peruerse, <hi>P.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which happely may faulct as much euen now as, raigning She:</l>
                  <pb n="345" facs="tcp:20257:10"/>
                  <l> Rests then by lawfull meanes Amisse in <hi>Pees</hi> amended be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now let vs briefly ouerrun vnto his present Throne,</l>
                  <l>That holds of God by Nature, Law, and Worth this Isle his owne,</l>
                  <l>The Stories Nationall of <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> once Kingdomes twaine</l>
                  <l>Within the same, the former long armipotent in vaine,</l>
                  <l>The latter altring now in Name through new-inlarged Raigne.</l>
                  <l>From These some doubt an Antidate of their arriuall Heere,</l>
                  <l>Of Those to haue been Pre-Regnants Authorities be cleere.</l>
                  <l>Mean while thy Lawds, <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> toucht Here touch short of thee,</l>
                  <l>Of Whom Posterities shall speake more gratefully than wee,</l>
                  <l>Would I could work vnto thy Worth, though then I ceast to bee.</l>
                  <l>But for we cannot saile thy Seas, our sailes we therefore strike,</l>
                  <l>And loth to leaue, of thee take leaue, that hast not left thy like.</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Picts, Scots, Welsh</hi> be now abridg'd, such Turnes as times did see,</l>
                  <l>Howbeit little Statrie, and among is mixed glee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 83.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether of <hi>Agathirsian Scythes,</hi> or <hi>Humbers</hi> Heere Remaigne,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Brutaines,</hi> braue Recusants of the Romane seruile Raigne,</l>
                  <l>(The last the Likeliest) were the <hi>Picts</hi> exact dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that will,</l>
                  <l>Those curious Ambiguities we leaue to others skill.</l>
                  <l>But briefly (for we must be briefe, since Enuie did prouide</l>
                  <l>Their fame, if possible their Name, from Historie to hide)</l>
                  <l>We shall the warlikenesse compend of those fame-wronged Men,</l>
                  <l>Obscur'd in all their Monuments by <hi>Scots,</hi> and curbd in Pen.</l>
                  <pb n="346" facs="tcp:20257:11"/>
                  <l> Yeat not the Legend proper to the <hi>Scots</hi> can wholy blanch</l>
                  <l>Their Mention, or thē name but needs their Prowesse must aduāce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Much owned of the <hi>English,</hi> all of <hi>Brutaines</hi> Continent</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> possesse, was then and ere that <hi>Ferquard</hi> Hither sent</l>
                  <l>The fatall Chaier, cald <hi>Penthland,</hi> till the <hi>Picts,</hi> a People stout,</l>
                  <l>Were by th'inuading <hi>Irish-Scots</hi> long thence debelled out.</l>
                  <l>But for we nam'd the fatall Chaier (the Stone we meane therein)</l>
                  <l>First whence, and how esteem'd we shall to calculate begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> (how truly censure as ye please) do father it</l>
                  <l>The Stone that <hi>Iacob,</hi> when as he from <hi>Esaus</hi> wroth did git,</l>
                  <l>Did sleepe vpon, whilst Angels on a Ladder came and went,</l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Messias</hi> from his Loynes was promis'd to be sent,</l>
                  <l>A iourney safe, a safe Returne, a broodious Issue, and</l>
                  <l>To them Confirmance to enioy all <hi>Canans</hi> happie Land.</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Gathelick</hi> from <hi>Egypt</hi> brought that Stone, their Stories say:</l>
                  <l>But if be askt how thither brought, why sufferd there to stay,</l>
                  <l>When long time after <hi>Moses</hi> Thence did <hi>Iacobs</hi> Seed conuay,</l>
                  <l>May thus be answred: <hi>Iacob,</hi> note (so ceremonious still</l>
                  <l>That to his Births, his Burials, euen his Wels, as good or ill</l>
                  <l>Did then and there betide, gaue names assining) not in this</l>
                  <l>On which he saw such Visions, had such Promises remisse.</l>
                  <l>For, saith the Text, he sacrifiz'd thereon, and named it</l>
                  <l>The House of God: nor, when returnd from <hi>Laban,</hi> did forgit</l>
                  <l>To pay his Vowes thereon, and had it still in high Esteeme:</l>
                  <l>At his Remoue to <hi>Egypt</hi> then from <hi>Canan</hi> may we deeme,</l>
                  <l>Amongst so many Carrages, he left it not behind.</l>
                  <l>But likely is his Seed, led Thence, There left it, for we finde</l>
                  <l>That, saue a Pittance fitting them Thence flying and pursew'd,</l>
                  <l>Not aught of Theirs they carrie he fore-warnd that all fore-vewd.</l>
                  <l>Their Legend hath, this <hi>Gathelus,</hi> to <hi>Pharaos</hi> daughter wed,</l>
                  <l>In whom the Plagues of <hi>Egypt</hi> for the <hi>Hebrues</hi> terror bred,</l>
                  <l>(For, saith the Text, with them also thence many Strangers fled)</l>
                  <l>Obseruant of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Rites solemniz'd on that Stone,</l>
                  <pb n="347" facs="tcp:20257:11"/>
                  <l> Vnto <hi>Gallicia</hi> (of his Name <hi>Port-Gathleck</hi> thenceforth knowne)</l>
                  <l>Transported it, the which his Seed did Thence to <hi>Ireland</hi> bring,</l>
                  <l>And Thence to <hi>Penthland,</hi> crowning thē on it their Heer-first-King.</l>
                  <l>First <hi>Edward</hi> wanne it Thence to vs, though Prophesies did sing:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Scotes sall bruke that Realme as natiue Ground:</l>
                  <l>Gif Weirds faile nocht) quhair eir this Chair is found.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gallicia, Ireland, Scotland,</hi> and now <hi>England,</hi> altering Name,</l>
                  <l>As seuerall Reuolutions thus of Time produc't the same,</l>
                  <l>Haue seene this Prophesie performd, by Destinie not ame.</l>
                  <l>Nor price nor prayer back from Hence this sacred Stone could win,</l>
                  <l>Which of our Coronations since the locall Rite hath bin.</l>
                  <l>Time, Place, and Persons too inferre some Likelihoods: they say</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Gatheleck</hi> was <hi>Cecrops</hi> sonne, that then in <hi>Greece</hi> did sway.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Pharao Achoris</hi> (whom they doe <hi>Bochoris</hi> mis-name)</l>
                  <l>Neere then ruld <hi>Egypt,</hi> Howbeit succeeded by the same</l>
                  <l>Heart-hardned <hi>Pharao, Chencres,</hi> whose pursute the Seas did tame.</l>
                  <l>The ancient <hi>Irish</hi> Manners and their Superstitions add,</l>
                  <l>Which, if conferd with <hi>Egypts,</hi> Thence may be intended hadd.</l>
                  <l>But, not without some Mysterie, both pretious and propitious,</l>
                  <l>Ere superstitious Papistrie, begeting Reliques vitious,</l>
                  <l>Had men mis-lead, thousand of yeeres this Stone was held, and is.</l>
                  <l>Howbeit pardon vs if here we intimate amis,</l>
                  <l>As sometimes Some, alluding Ours it winding to the taile</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Troies Palladium</hi> hailed from the <hi>Greekes</hi> to <hi>Ilions</hi> baile.</l>
                  <l>But also with the Shrine the Saint we presently possesse,</l>
                  <l>Vniting Crownes, <hi>Scotch</hi> Prophesies performed nerthelesse.</l>
                  <l>But what of Prophesies? t'is God effecteth all in all:</l>
                  <l>Our Fathers longed for this Day: may we it happie call.</l>
                  <l>And happie <hi>Mary</hi> hadst thou bin, and it both Kingdomes good,</l>
                  <l>Had not false friends thy Marrage Here with our yong Prince with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood.</l>
                  <l>But it effecteth in thy Sonne that in thy selfe did faile,</l>
                  <l>And where we feard tēpestuous Gusts we hope a prosperous Gaile.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iames, Io-Pean</hi> sing we thee: long liue, raigne, and preuaile.</l>
                  <pb n="348" facs="tcp:20257:12"/>
                  <l> No doubt from Natures Secrets Spirits teach admirable skill,</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>Sagist, Lamist, Strigist</hi> though, or <hi>Pythonist</hi> that will.</l>
                  <l>I haue (not superstitiously) obserued times not few</l>
                  <l>Old <hi>Wordings,</hi> which vnhapned are vnheeded, prouing trew:</l>
                  <l>Mongst others, worth the note, an old &amp; common Speech in <hi>Ware:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where Men, askt idly it whereof the Asker might despare,</l>
                  <l>Would answer, that performance should or paiment be, <hi>When as</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>the King comes vnto Wiggen:</hi> And that comming came to pas</l>
                  <l>When first he entred <hi>Ware,</hi> euen when it vnexpected was.</l>
                  <l>So base a Cottage once, but now vsde with a better Thing,</l>
                  <l>Begot that saying first: thus Time with it doth wonders bring:</l>
                  <l>They liue did word it many yeeres ere hapt or borne this King.</l>
                  <l>* More serious this: his Highnesse then a Tenderling, did I</l>
                  <l>(A Puple) reade, wrote time past kens, of him this Prophesie,</l>
                  <l>Or call it as yee please, that Terme Clerks to these Times denie:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Post Iacobum Iacobus, Iacobum Iacobus, quoque Quintus,</l>
                  <l>At sextus Iacobus Regno regnabit vtroque.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>After a <hi>Iames</hi> shall be a <hi>Iames,</hi> a third <hi>Iames,</hi> and a Fourth,</l>
                  <l>A fift <hi>Iames</hi> also, but the Sixt shall sway the Scepters both.</l>
                  <l>Besides three youthfull Queens that stop that Currant likely might,</l>
                  <l>Great Interruptions, ouer-blowne, we also could recite.</l>
                  <l>But by the Deitie it so was destinate, and who</l>
                  <l>Reioyceth not that that great worke of God is not to doe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How Hence, with more than much adoe, the <hi>Scots</hi> at last expell</l>
                  <l>The Here predominating <hi>Picts</hi> ensueth now to tell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="chapter">
               <pb n="349" facs="tcp:20257:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 84.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen from the <hi>Hebredes</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> had footing in this Isle,</l>
                  <l>They and the <hi>Picts</hi> allie and held in peacefull League a while:</l>
                  <l>So populous, so circumspect, in Walls and Armes so strong,</l>
                  <l>That of such Neighbourhood the <hi>Brutes</hi> so ielious were of wrong,</l>
                  <l>As gainst the wilinesse of These, and warliknesse of Those,</l>
                  <l>They more affected Policie than hazarding of blowes:</l>
                  <l>Fore-seeing such Combinement might their Enuie ouermatch.</l>
                  <l>A fained Ambasie therefore they to the <hi>Picts</hi> dispatch:</l>
                  <l>With blandishments, like <hi>Aesops</hi> Fox deluding <hi>Aesops</hi> Crow,</l>
                  <l>The hansell of their Scepter new congratulating so,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Britons</hi> Wealth and Prowse also they arrogated such,</l>
                  <l>And from the <hi>Scots</hi> by Contraries did derogate so much,</l>
                  <l>Remembring (which the <hi>Picts</hi> themselues could not forget) the day</l>
                  <l>In Oracle, when Thence the <hi>Scots</hi> should driue the <hi>Picts</hi> away,</l>
                  <l>With many like Atractiues and Ditractions to and fro,</l>
                  <l>As none but <hi>Brutaine</hi> now was friend, and none but <hi>Scotland</hi> foe.</l>
                  <l>Anon through <hi>Penthland</hi> was proclam'd Auoidance in short space</l>
                  <l>Of euery <hi>Scot</hi> on paine of death: wherefore like law tooke place</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Scotland</hi> also: neither part the punishment omit</l>
                  <l>That might inflict the Penaltie, the <hi>Britons</hi> glad of it.</l>
                  <l>Whereby from Riots did it grow to Termes of open warre,</l>
                  <l>The which with Aides vnto the <hi>Picts</hi> the <hi>Brutons</hi> did prefarre.</l>
                  <l>But Things seem'd then more intricate than that the <hi>Scots</hi> alone</l>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="chapter">
               <pb n="352" facs="tcp:20257:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yeat oft it haps, by how much more high Dignities preferre,</l>
                  <l>So much the more, though lesse secure, men liue irreguler:</l>
                  <l>But Insolencie hath a time aswell to fall as erre,</l>
                  <l>To which no Opportunities but doe Effects efferre:</l>
                  <l>Then, breathing Clods, from Actions ill let ill Euents deterre.</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Dowall,</hi> There then gratious, slew this <hi>Nathak</hi> at the last,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Rewthar,</hi> wedded to the King of <hi>Penthlands</hi> daughter, plac't</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Scotlands</hi> Throne, howbeit in Minoritie: wherefore</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Ferquhard,</hi> for this law infring'd, brought all things in vprore.</l>
                  <l>Or rather vnder this pretex he drifted soueraigne Sway,</l>
                  <l>Whereto did this Occasion seeme to him a troden way:</l>
                  <l>And former Popularitie, whereto Ambition weads,</l>
                  <l>Had furnisht him of plebale Friends, a Beast of many heads.</l>
                  <l>On which, as if on <hi>Pegasus,</hi> ambitious Gallants ride,</l>
                  <l>Though it an euer-break-neck haue such forged <hi>Persees</hi> tride.</l>
                  <l>Vnhappie Popularitie, that like to <hi>Aesops</hi> Ape</l>
                  <l>With culling kils thy Darlings, whilst the lesser loued scape:</l>
                  <l>Senselesse Ambition, that forgets or not obserues at all</l>
                  <l>That, if not selfe-Straines, Policie must temporize thy fall:</l>
                  <l>Fond Vulgers, that a <hi>Phaëton</hi> a <hi>Phoebus</hi> vse to call:</l>
                  <l>For in bi-fronted <hi>Ianus</hi> is your Science none or small.</l>
                  <l>Well, howsoeuer, <hi>Ferquhard</hi> troupes the flower of <hi>Scotlands</hi> Prowse:</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Penthlands</hi> Chiualrie no lesse of <hi>Dowals</hi> act allowes.</l>
                  <l>Now either People had displaide their Onsets, and was fought</l>
                  <l>A Battell, dearer than the which no Souldiours euer bought,</l>
                  <l>For slaughter as perseuerent as may be said or thought.</l>
                  <l>Whereby their either Kingdome heere some following yeeres did faile:</l>
                  <l>For, in this Disaduantage, them the <hi>Britons</hi> did assaile,</l>
                  <l>And did the <hi>Scots</hi> to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the <hi>Picts</hi> to <hi>Orkney</hi> chase:</l>
                  <l>Where either liued in Exile, till altred thus the case.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Impatiently they twice sixe yeeres Prescription Hence endure,</l>
                  <l>When with such Forces as they had, although but small yeat sure,</l>
                  <l>They (met of such forelorned Soules y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> since their Countries wrack,</l>
                  <pb n="353" facs="tcp:20257:13"/>
                  <l> Remote from Men, in Woods and Caues had liu'd in fearfull lack)</l>
                  <l>Returne, and with those despret Bands, incountering their foes,</l>
                  <l>Had now the better of the Field: Whence this Attonement groes:</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Picts</hi> their owne, as earst, should amplie reposseed</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Iulius Caesars</hi> Entrie, so of Warres this Isle was freed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Him to resist, that out of <hi>Fraunce</hi> the <hi>Britons</hi> did inuaide,</l>
                  <l>Came <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> repelling Hence the <hi>Romaines</hi> by their aide.</l>
                  <l>Howbeit, in the following yeare he wonne a Tribute hence,</l>
                  <l>Which might haue faild him, had as earst concur'd the <hi>Picts</hi> defence.</l>
                  <l>As yet the Northern Regions search the <hi>Romaines</hi> did neglect,</l>
                  <l>Vntill (vnto whose Ruines none can certainly direct,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Penthlands</hi> pride for stately Towers &amp; strength of walls pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vespasian</hi> wonne <hi>Camelon,</hi> still hild <hi>Romes,</hi> till <hi>Rome</hi> there ended.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bellona</hi> seemed in this Ile her Residence to haue:</l>
                  <l>Where, of three Scepters, scarcely one it selfe afoote could saue.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Romaines,</hi> vnder diuers of their <hi>Caesars-</hi>selues, but still</l>
                  <l>The worthiest of their Generals this Ile with Armes did fill</l>
                  <l>At diuers times, with diuers change of good and bad euent,</l>
                  <l>But to it tackling euer found vndanted <hi>Penthland</hi> bent.</l>
                  <l>For when the <hi>Britons</hi> were subdewd, and <hi>Caratack</hi> the Scot,</l>
                  <l>That for his Courage and Conduct continued glorie got,</l>
                  <l>Euen then and nerethelesse the <hi>Picts</hi> did not in courage quaile,</l>
                  <l>But, oft Victorious, of themselues the <hi>Romaines</hi> did assaile:</l>
                  <l>Hence chacing some their Presidents, and some their Legions slue:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Romaines</hi> would not giue thē peace, and could them not subdue.</l>
                  <l>Who, brauely breaking thus the Ise to <hi>Scots,</hi> their old Consorts,</l>
                  <l>Both twaine made hauock of their foes, demolishing their Forts,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Romaines</hi> now in either Land were dispossessed quite,</l>
                  <l>And, drifting oft Reentries, oft repented them of fight.</l>
                  <l>Heere only <hi>Brutaine</hi> hild for <hi>Rome,</hi> and many yeares from thence</l>
                  <l>Arm'd still against the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> with losse for recompence.</l>
                  <l>But leauing <hi>Romaines</hi> thrilled thence, and <hi>Brutes</hi> by <hi>Rome</hi> opprest,</l>
                  <l>What hapt meane while betwixt the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> shall be digest.</l>
                  <pb n="354" facs="tcp:20257:14"/>
                  <l> How <hi>Brutons</hi> chased hence the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> it hath been said:</l>
                  <l>And toucht shalbe how These thrald Those, for all their <hi>Romain</hi> aid.</l>
                  <l>Ensueth first how <hi>Picts</hi> draue hence the <hi>Scots,</hi> though <hi>Scots</hi> at last</l>
                  <l>Extirpt the <hi>Picts:</hi> for worser heere then Fortunes Lotterie past.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 86.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Retious is Peace, yet be obseru'd how warlike Nations oft</l>
                  <l>Haue thereby than by outward Armes more Inconuenience cought:</l>
                  <l>These two bellosious People cleer'd no sooner forren swords,</l>
                  <l>But euery Toy a Trumpet to some ciuill Broyle affords.</l>
                  <l>Nor could their Northerne Climate brooke two Suns in it to shine,</l>
                  <l>For sometime This, and sometime That did violently decline.</l>
                  <l>But, passing by their either oft Domesticke Discords great,</l>
                  <l>Of either Kingdome shouldering the other we intreate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The former Lawe, disabling all in Nonage <hi>Scotlands</hi> Raigne,</l>
                  <l>By three competing Gardenship was now in tearmes againe.</l>
                  <l>Of which one <hi>Romaks</hi> (also of the <hi>Picts</hi> bloods-royall) Plea</l>
                  <l>Was swords, not words, and did of <hi>Scots</hi> by <hi>Picts</hi> great numbers slea:</l>
                  <l>For which both he and <hi>Picts</hi> became so odious to the <hi>Scots,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As to destroy both him (then King) and them they sleepe no Plots.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Romaks</hi> Entrie, so his Raigne tyrannous was, vntill</l>
                  <l>His Nobles did conspire, and him by armes pursued kill:</l>
                  <l>Against the <hi>Picts</hi> their Power as yet inabled not their will.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore to them, preparing then Reuenge for <hi>Romaks</hi> death,</l>
                  <l>They sent Excuses: but in vaine their Legates spent their breath.</l>
                  <pb n="355" facs="tcp:20257:14"/>
                  <l> Saue Armor would no answere serue the <hi>Picts:</hi> whereof did grow</l>
                  <l>A Battle fearce, where either tooke and gaue the ouerthrow:</l>
                  <l>For both their Kings did perish, &amp; with bloud the fields did flow.</l>
                  <l>Vnto the <hi>Picts</hi> succeeded though the better of that fight:</l>
                  <l>But shortly after with the like the <hi>Scots</hi> did them requite.</l>
                  <l>With such perseuerant hatred and ferocitie they both</l>
                  <l>Afflict each other, as but bloud might qualifie their wroth:</l>
                  <l>Vntill the <hi>Picts</hi> (impacable, say <hi>Scots,</hi> by <hi>Romaines</hi> aide)</l>
                  <l>Disseizen of the scottish Raigne within this Ile had made.</l>
                  <l>And whosoeuer, if a Scot, that howsoeuer kept</l>
                  <l>Themselues vnslaughtred was exild, no Sexe or Age except</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romak, Angusian, Fethelmak,</hi> and <hi>Eugen</hi> did succeed</l>
                  <l>In Septer and in slaughter: And of <hi>Pict-</hi>kings three we reade</l>
                  <l>Succeedingly then also slaine in this infestious strife:</l>
                  <l>And of a pitious Storie of King <hi>Eugens</hi> widowed wife:</l>
                  <l>Also of <hi>Hergest</hi> King of <hi>Picts,</hi> too much to Rigor bent,</l>
                  <l>In banishing the <hi>Scots,</hi> the which himselfe did soone repent.</l>
                  <l>For, whilst he thought to him and his no safetie vnlesse</l>
                  <l>All scotsh-Soules from their bodies or their Soile he dispossesse,</l>
                  <l>By curious search <hi>Cartangis,</hi> Queene to <hi>Eugen</hi> slaughtred late,</l>
                  <l>Like to a second <hi>Hecuba</hi> condoling <hi>Priams</hi> fate,</l>
                  <l>Was haled from her husbands Tombe, washt with her hartie teares:</l>
                  <l>Who, when before Prince <hi>Maximus</hi> the Romaine she appeares,</l>
                  <l>And was demaunded why she had against the Edict staide,</l>
                  <l>The bewtious Queene, with teares among, this sober Answer made.</l>
                  <l>I am, quoth she, of husband, friends, riches, and hope bereft,</l>
                  <l>And by how much the more I thus in Miserie am left,</l>
                  <l>So much the lesse am to be feard: ah, then me thinks my foes</l>
                  <l>Might brooke my Presence, at the least to sport them in my woes.</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Brutaine,</hi> where my Father rules, shall see me thus deiect:</l>
                  <l>Then giue me death in <hi>Scotland,</hi> els my dying life protect.</l>
                  <l>The valerous Romaine President, commiserating her,</l>
                  <l>Besides Exilement pardoned, he richly did prefer</l>
                  <pb n="356" facs="tcp:20257:15"/>
                  <l> The good distressed Lady. But the <hi>Picts</hi> enuying it,</l>
                  <l>Dispoyled Her and Hers, and did els-what too much vnfit:</l>
                  <l>Nor on the Felons to do Lawe did <hi>Maximus</hi> omit.</l>
                  <l>Whereat, so farforth as he might, King <hi>Hergest</hi> then repinde:</l>
                  <l>And how he added <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>Romes</hi> Empire puts in minde</l>
                  <l>The President, whom nerethelesse the Queene did gratious finde,</l>
                  <l>And, mauger <hi>Hergest,</hi> her abode in <hi>Scotland</hi> he assignde.</l>
                  <l>There did she daylie Obsequies vnto her Husbands Ghoste,</l>
                  <l>And prayed for their valiant Soules that perisht in his hoste.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Also King <hi>Hergest</hi> him bethinks of his late error now,</l>
                  <l>When more nor lesse he could than as the <hi>Romaines</hi> him allow:</l>
                  <l>And for his old confedrate friends the <hi>Scots</hi> was ill apaide,</l>
                  <l>In whose exile he had himselfe and his to <hi>Rome</hi> betraide.</l>
                  <l>For where as they, combined, gaue euen to the <hi>Romaines</hi> peace;</l>
                  <l>To either People now, disioynd, did wonted freedome cease:</l>
                  <l>Small things by Concord prosper, great by Discord do decrease.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Picts</hi> Succession to the Crowne, their auncient lawes and all</l>
                  <l>Were by the <hi>Romaines</hi> disanuld, and nought brought in but thrall:</l>
                  <l>In which respect the Suffrings of the <hi>Scots</hi> to theirs were small.</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Hergest,</hi> whose great spirit could no Seruitude abide,</l>
                  <l>Inuolued in Impatience, stabd himselfe, and so he dide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By this vnhappy Quarrell thus eight Kings were made away,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scotland</hi> no Kingdome then, and this of <hi>Penthland</hi> in decay,</l>
                  <l>Two forren Armies fell that to restore the <hi>Scots</hi> assay.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="chapter">
               <pb n="357" facs="tcp:20257:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 87.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Scots,</hi> that more than fortie yeares had been in hard Exile,</l>
                  <l>Were by the <hi>Picts,</hi> that vnder-went the <hi>Romaine</hi> yoke meane while,</l>
                  <l>Recal'd by double Ambasie: who, though they were disperst,</l>
                  <l>By labourd Opportunities of their returne conuerst.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fergus</hi> (a fatall name vnto the <hi>Scots</hi> beginning-Raigne,</l>
                  <l>And why not This their first king here, &amp; <hi>Scots</hi> for <hi>Gothes</hi> mistain?)</l>
                  <l>One neerest of the blood, who then in <hi>Denmarke</hi> did remaine,</l>
                  <l>That with the <hi>Gothes</hi> had sacked <hi>Rome,</hi> and Thence brought wealth &amp; fame,</l>
                  <l>Collects an Armie, and arriues in <hi>Scotland</hi> with the same.</l>
                  <l>To whom assemble soone the <hi>Picts,</hi> and, Quarrels passed-by,</l>
                  <l>Against the <hi>Romaines</hi> Either did their forces whole applye:</l>
                  <l>And in their Territories slew and made their foes to flye.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Victorine</hi> (then either Realme to <hi>Rome</hi> in Prouince was,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Britaine</hi> too) thither, to stay their forward Swords, did passe</l>
                  <l>Of Romefied <hi>Britons</hi> and Emperials warre so great,</l>
                  <l>As, after bloodie Battels, coold theirs and those others heate.</l>
                  <l>For both their Armies, broken with these Battels, did returne:</l>
                  <l>Esteeming it in vaine as yet against the Prick to spurne.</l>
                  <l>Meane while in friendly League the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> together liue,</l>
                  <l>And Skermidges both of and to their foes did take and giue.</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Placidus,</hi> by <hi>Victorine</hi> for <hi>Rome</hi> Deputed then,</l>
                  <l>Fought with the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> vnto the losse of most his men.</l>
                  <l>To either Propriarie so was either Realme againe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Romaines</hi> left, to leaue their holds to saue their liues then faine.</l>
                  <pb n="358" facs="tcp:20257:16"/>
                  <l> Yet both their Kings in following fight did brauely tyne their liues:</l>
                  <l>Whence long the <hi>Romaine</hi> cause against the Armes cōfedrat thriues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But neuer did the <hi>Picts</hi> omit occasion when they might</l>
                  <l>Reuenge them on th'Emperiales by their Stratigmes or fight.</l>
                  <l>In fine, the <hi>Romaine</hi> Monarchie Els-where did languish so,</l>
                  <l>As their disabled Conquests heere they of themselues forgo.</l>
                  <l>Reforming first their thrise-reard wall of fourescore miles in length,</l>
                  <l>Against the <hi>Picts</hi> defencelesse, though of wondrous Art &amp; strength:</l>
                  <l>When thence▪forth long the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> did <hi>Brutaine</hi> so inthrall,</l>
                  <l>As lastly in their Ayde they did the <hi>Saxons</hi> hither call.</l>
                  <l>Who, by Degrees (the <hi>Welsh</hi> except, so named <hi>Saxonlie)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Subdued <hi>Brutaine (England</hi> now) vnto their Soueraigntie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The lacerated Empire of the <hi>Romaines,</hi> though with griefe,</l>
                  <l>Disclaim'd the <hi>Brutaines,</hi> at the least could yeeld them no reliefe.</l>
                  <l>Imbellious through their Policie, adde Pestilence thereto,</l>
                  <l>Succeeded with th'vnlabourd Earths sterilitie: but who</l>
                  <l>Wold think that Plētie more offence thā war, death, dearth, should do?</l>
                  <l>The Earth then fertile, men became effeminat and vaine,</l>
                  <l>Luxurious, Idle, <hi>Bacchanists,</hi> and gladly intertaine,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Issachres,</hi> their Seruitude, Their foes but aske and haue</l>
                  <l>Conditions such as they themselues, how grosse someuer, craue,</l>
                  <l>Tribute, with Pledges at the <hi>Picts</hi> their owne Deuotion: so</l>
                  <l>A sensuall, seruile, sinfull life the <hi>Brutons</hi> vnder-go.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> Policie, in plentie Sloth, and ciuill Discords heere</l>
                  <l>From that it was, brought <hi>Brutaine</hi> thus to Nullitie wellneere.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Brutons</hi> (diffrent <hi>Brutons</hi> from your Auncestors, that oft</l>
                  <l>Victoriously gainst these your Foes and <hi>Romaine</hi> Legions fought:</l>
                  <l>Who, had ye neuer been secure, had neuer you subdude,</l>
                  <l>Nor needed on th' <hi>Armoricanes</hi> that Raigne ye should obtrude)</l>
                  <l>Euen now for then I should be greeu'd at your dis<hi>-brittish't</hi> swords,</l>
                  <l>But that your then resumed Prowse, when <hi>Welsh</hi> amends affords.</l>
                  <l>And, that your <hi>Arthure</hi> comes againe, so far-forth we allow</l>
                  <l>It Prophesie, as <hi>Brutaine</hi> dead with him reuiueth now:</l>
                  <pb n="359" facs="tcp:20257:16"/>
                  <l> That is, <hi>Brutes</hi> Baptisme of this Ile, that ana-baptizd grew</l>
                  <l>By diuers names in diuers parts, <hi>Iames</hi> doth through-out renew.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Arthur Tuder</hi> was your Prince, and yee, inthrald before,</l>
                  <l>Were then infranchiz'd one with vs adds it fulfild the more.</l>
                  <l>But to our <hi>Brutes,</hi> in mind deiect and warr-bit, be progrest.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 88.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome (not degenerated though) oft instanted the rest,</l>
                  <l>To imitate their Auncestors, and Slothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse detest:</l>
                  <l>By rightfull Armour to remaund Theirs of their foes possest,</l>
                  <l>Their liues to better, with their foes couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to cope,</l>
                  <l>Not to be Fortunes Infidels, but better times to hope.</l>
                  <l>Which Counsell wrought, &amp; soone their foes had newes how they conspire,</l>
                  <l>It being to the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> fresh fewell to their fire.</l>
                  <l>For, hearing <hi>Constantine</hi> with his french<hi>-Britons</hi> now ashore,</l>
                  <l>And all reuolted heere from them, for first Reuenge therefore</l>
                  <l>They slew the <hi>brittish</hi> Pledges: Then conuent their Forces all,</l>
                  <l>And with the <hi>Brutaines</hi> fought a Field, to Eithers losse not small.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>Constantine</hi> th' <hi>Armoricane,</hi> of <hi>Brutaine</hi> now made King,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>scotch</hi> King slaine, and <hi>Picts</hi> repeld, did both to reason bring.</l>
                  <l>And disciplind in martiall and in morall Practise his,</l>
                  <l>Till him a <hi>Pict</hi> did murther: Nor like death his Sonne did misse,</l>
                  <l>By trecherie of <hi>Vortiger,</hi> that his Successor is.</l>
                  <l>How, odious to his Subiects, he inuits the <hi>Saxons</hi> aid,</l>
                  <l>Who thence till now haue Lorded heere, it hath els-where bin said.</l>
               </lg>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="chapter">
               <pb n="362" facs="tcp:20257:17"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Faire Virgin, quoth he, ouer-faire to be a Virgin euer,</l>
                  <l>Although a Recluse yet to be a Relaps feare thou neuer:</l>
                  <l>Increase and multiplie, saith God: or should but <hi>Nature</hi> preach,</l>
                  <l>Assure thee such a Votaresse might iustifie a breach.</l>
                  <l>I dare absolue thee of thy vow, on perill of my Soule,</l>
                  <l>That am as thou a Regular, but now farewell my Cowle.</l>
                  <l>Then like himselfe he shewd himselfe Gallant euery way,</l>
                  <l>And did by Art, gifts, Eloquence, and what not her assay?</l>
                  <l>But all in vaine, so opposite to Loue did she perseuer,</l>
                  <l>As that vnto his Pandresse Arte he was enforc't to leaue her.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now by your blessed Beades, quoth she, your self you quitted well</l>
                  <l>Against his importunitie. Yet this I must you tell:</l>
                  <l>He is a proper Gentleman, sharp witted, sweet of hauour,</l>
                  <l>Of good parts, great possessions, and well worthy of your fauour.</l>
                  <l>Amongst your Sisterhood I know are amorous Wenches some,</l>
                  <l>But for they are professed I must reuerently be domme:</l>
                  <l>For she that Sainct-seems, lookes demure, turns vp the white of eie,</l>
                  <l>At Shrifts and clergie-Standings can a common-Place applie,</l>
                  <l>Hers Indenotion, not to be Deuotion were a lie.</l>
                  <l>So powerfull is Religion as, but cloaking vnder it,</l>
                  <l>Auoyds to be expresly taxt of want-zeale, or want-wit.</l>
                  <l>Your superstitious vowes, if broke, at most are veniall sinne:</l>
                  <l>Or rather, kept, you do gainst God and Nature fault therein.</l>
                  <l>Admit the Gentleman should speed, should I against it spurne?</l>
                  <l>No, not to let it were lesse fault than still to let him burne.</l>
                  <l>Poore Girles (not Gods) but few of you so sainctified I know,</l>
                  <l>But sometimes to coniectures of Concupiscence ye grow.</l>
                  <l>And what prouoking more thereto than liues which yee do leade,</l>
                  <l>In pleasant Mansions, idle Ease, selfe-Pranking, fill of bread?</l>
                  <l>And lustie flesh takes little keepe of letting fall a Beade,</l>
                  <l>But into Sinnes restraind vs most so much the more doth leade.</l>
                  <l>If needs you will that marriage nor mens loue shall you allure,</l>
                  <l>Nature and Vowes are tempted oft, but <hi>Guanors</hi> Tombe makes sure:</l>
                  <pb n="363" facs="tcp:20257:17"/>
                  <l> (Was thither by the Trot traind forth the Nouesse, so to proue</l>
                  <l>Whether she would a Virgin die, or might be hoped loue)</l>
                  <l>That you by Nature should be chaste (the Contrarie who not?)</l>
                  <l>I hardly can beleeue: but if? what harme I pray were got,</l>
                  <l>If should you tread vpō her Tombe, whence Barrennesse doth gro,</l>
                  <l>And end of amorous Burnings, since your vow importeth so?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Nunne, that euermore had heard and held it as her Creed,</l>
                  <l>That she that trod vpon that Tombe of such Euent should speed,</l>
                  <l>Did blush (and blame her not that so was put vnto her shifts)</l>
                  <l>Thus on the Beldame did retort instance of her owne drifts.</l>
                  <l>Mother, quoth she, good manners were the Elder former go.</l>
                  <l>What I, that hope a husband, nor despaire of issue? (So</l>
                  <l>An Aunchanter than I hath had) by sweet Saint <hi>Pancrace,</hi> no,</l>
                  <l>The old-wife said. Nor, quoth the Nunne, meane I to be the furst</l>
                  <l>Of this our Age treads on that Tombe to women so accurst.</l>
                  <l>But thus a possibilitie of yeelding from the Nunne,</l>
                  <l>And by the subtle Exorcist of prizing being wonne,</l>
                  <l>They back returne, that at the Tombe more durst not than was done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She, that at least so blur'd an Eie, for battle fought and all,</l>
                  <l>Euen to sollicite earnestly, on such fresh hope, did fall.</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Cresida</hi> scornd <hi>Troilus</hi> and <hi>Plauges</hi> had manifold,</l>
                  <l>How oft the Goblin <hi>Incubus</hi> Loue-wronged had contrould,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Iphis</hi> for the <hi>Cyprian</hi> Lasse fore-did himselfe she tould.</l>
                  <l>Like tales and Metamorphosies passe many in this chat:</l>
                  <l>Nor lackt the Ballad of the Maid transformed to a Cat,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Arthurs</hi> Queene, there tombd, so doombd, for falsed loue, fell pat.</l>
                  <l>So many Incantations, lyes, feares, hopes, instanced shee,</l>
                  <l>With amorous Sonners feelingly of passion and loues glee,</l>
                  <l>As lastly did the <hi>non-plust</hi> Nunne vnto her Charmes agree.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But leauing <hi>Guanora</hi> her Tombe, and none on it to tread,</l>
                  <l>(For Women be nor Fooles, nor Saincts) ensueth now to reade,</l>
                  <l>(Which asks a tragick Penne to write) the dire downe-fall of those</l>
                  <l>That florished so long and found at last too bitter foes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="chapter">
               <pb n="364" facs="tcp:20257:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 90.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Charles</hi> the Great for <hi>France</hi> of <hi>Scots</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedracie obtain'd</l>
                  <l>Of mutuall aides against <hi>English,</hi> which hath thence till now remain'd,</l>
                  <l>Els, likely, ouer either Realme long since had <hi>England</hi> raign'd,</l>
                  <l>At least by intermariage, still by that Compact restraind:</l>
                  <l>For nere hild League lesse violate or permanent like while,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>French</hi> rescuing <hi>Scots,</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> abrode and in this Isle:</l>
                  <l>Which God, in Nature now and law dissoluing, ill appayes</l>
                  <l>Enuious <hi>Fraunce</hi> it selfe that helpt and harmed vs that wayes:</l>
                  <l>Who questions then an Vnion that such inconuenience stayes?</l>
                  <l>What Nation seuers Policie where One one Land obayes?</l>
                  <l>Our Elders opportuned like occasion hereunto,</l>
                  <l>When whatsoeuer they had done that League did still vndoo:</l>
                  <l>No maruell, selfe-securitie <hi>France</hi> in that loue did woo:</l>
                  <l>But be an Vnion perfected, and storme it skils not who.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scot,</hi> I say, him to secure of <hi>Picts,</hi> refusing so</l>
                  <l>To tripertite that League, did wed (whence <hi>Penthlands</hi> ouerthro)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fergusia, Hungust</hi> King of <hi>Picts</hi> his sister: <hi>Alpine,</hi> sonne</l>
                  <l>Of this said Marriage, challenge to the <hi>Pictish</hi> Throne begun.</l>
                  <l>Which, had it not bin destinate to <hi>Scots,</hi> had neuer bin,</l>
                  <l>Behou'd such obstacles to be disperst ere it they win,</l>
                  <l>Nor swords more resolute than theirs could counterpleade therin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Achaius, Alpins</hi> father dead, were inter-Regnants twaine</l>
                  <l>Succeedingly ere <hi>Alpine</hi> was by lawe enabled Raigne.</l>
                  <pb n="365" facs="tcp:20257:18"/>
                  <l> Both dying issulesse, to him did <hi>Scotlands</hi> Crowne accrew:</l>
                  <l>Who also, from his Mother, claime to <hi>Penthland</hi> did pursew:</l>
                  <l>Where, though he ends disastrously, two ante-Kings he slew.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Penthland</hi> was no easie taske to win, though lastly wonne,</l>
                  <l>Yet with the losse on either part of many a mothers sonne.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Picts</hi> distasted nothing more than that a forren birth</l>
                  <l>Should them subiect, rather than which they all had vowed death.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> also in <hi>Alpins</hi> right had all oblig'd their blood:</l>
                  <l>Nor more was sworne on either side than whereunto they stood.</l>
                  <l>Succeedingly two <hi>Pict-</hi>Kings fell in two such bloodie fields,</l>
                  <l>As was indifferent whether part subdude, for neither yeelds:</l>
                  <l>But either, sadly for their slaine, and gladly for returne,</l>
                  <l>Retier their weakned Forces that in wisht reuenge did burne.</l>
                  <l>When season serued <hi>Alpine</hi> soone did recollect his Armes:</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Brudus</hi> King of <hi>Picts</hi> likewise his fierie people swarmes.</l>
                  <l>More resolutely than these two no Armies euer met,</l>
                  <l>Nor Captaines that mens courages more thā these Kings did whet.</l>
                  <l>When long was fought on either part with doubtfull warres euent,</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Brudus</hi> side the better of that bloudie bargaine went.</l>
                  <l>No ransoming of <hi>Scots,</hi> but all subdued then were slaine:</l>
                  <l>In which vnchancie battell was King <hi>Alpine</hi> Prisnor taine:</l>
                  <l>From whom, first manacled, they hewd his better-worthy head,</l>
                  <l>And pold it on their Citie walls for signe how <hi>Scots</hi> had spead.</l>
                  <l>O too too erred iolitie, and insolencie strange,</l>
                  <l>Transporting <hi>Fortunes</hi> wantons past expectance of a change.</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Scots</hi> impatiently indur'd such View of their disgrace,</l>
                  <l>Who faind them <hi>Picts,</hi> and gaining so conuenient time and place,</l>
                  <l>Conuaied thence King <hi>Alpins</hi> head, well guerdond of his sonne:</l>
                  <l>By whom to renouate the Warres his Nobles thus were wonne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their former losse dishartned them so much that when, in vaine,</l>
                  <l>He oft had wowd their aids, he seemd expectant to remaine:</l>
                  <l>Conuenting, as for other cause, them, feasted, and prouides</l>
                  <l>Their Lodgings in his Pallace, and in euery Chamber hides</l>
                  <pb n="366" facs="tcp:20257:19"/>
                  <l> One clad in fishes scales, a club of Muscane in one hand,</l>
                  <l>In th'other was a bugle horne, and all at midnight stand</l>
                  <l>Before each sleeping Nobles bed, &amp; through the horne thus spake.</l>
                  <l>* Thou scottish <hi>Heros,</hi> at the least to God his Angell wake:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Kenneth</hi> your King must be obaid, and <hi>Picts</hi> be ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>* Assist him lest thou perish now th'Almighties will is knowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The wakened Lords beleeud that Voyce not humaine, &amp; behild,</l>
                  <l>(For naturally that wood in darke giues Shine, which now had fild</l>
                  <l>Each roome) the vision, in a tryse that vanished, for when</l>
                  <l>The wood and scales were hid was all in sudden darkenesse then.</l>
                  <l>This voyce and vision did affright the Nobles, and next day</l>
                  <l>Each vnto other did the same in secrecie bewray:</l>
                  <l>All iump of one same time, sight, speach, and therefore all beleeue</l>
                  <l>It was from God, and for the warres so long delayed greeue:</l>
                  <l>The King did fraine their whisprings, and themselues to him they shreeue.</l>
                  <l>Who likewise did affirme himselfe so visited that night:</l>
                  <l>By which Elusion all were brought against the <hi>Picts</hi> to fight.</l>
                  <l>Like guiles were frequent in those dayes, so Exorcists and Friers</l>
                  <l>Confirmd in superstition men, and spead their owne desires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of <hi>Fairies, Goblins,</hi> walking Lights, &amp; like chat Grandams much,</l>
                  <l>Nor am my selfe incredulous that haue bin, and be such:</l>
                  <l>Yet sauoreth, me thinks, a Lie this that of late befell,</l>
                  <l>Which, though report should fable, is no harmefull iest to tell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="chapter">
               <pb n="367" facs="tcp:20257:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 91.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Shepheard, whilst his Flock did feede, him in his Cloke did wrap,</l>
                  <l>Bids Patch his Dog stand Sentenell, both to secure a nap,</l>
                  <l>And lest his Bagpipe, Sheephooke, Skrip, and Bottell (most his wealth)</l>
                  <l>By Vagrants (more then many now) might suffer of their stealth.</l>
                  <l>As he twixt sleepe and waking lay against a greene Banks side,</l>
                  <l>A Round of <hi>Fairie-Elues,</hi> and <hi>Larrs</hi> of other kind, he spide:</l>
                  <l>Who in their dancing him so charm'd, that though he wakt he slept,</l>
                  <l>Now Pincht they him, antickt about, and on, and off him lept.</l>
                  <l>Mongst them, of bigger bulke and voyce, a bare-breecht <hi>Goblin</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>That at their Gamboles laughed, like the braying of an Asse.</l>
                  <l>At once the Shepherds Bagpipe (for they also vsed it)</l>
                  <l>Was husht, and round about him they, as if in Councell, sit.</l>
                  <l>Vpon whose face the breechlesse <hi>Larr</hi> did set his buttocks bare,</l>
                  <l>Bespeaking thus his beau-Compeers, like <hi>Caiphas</hi> in his Chaire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Poore <hi>Robin-good-fellow,</hi> sweet Elfs, much thanks you for this glee,</l>
                  <l>Since last I came into this Land a Raritie to see:</l>
                  <l>When Nunnes, Monks, Friers, and Votaries were here of euery sort,</l>
                  <l>We were accustomed, ye wot, to this and merrier sport.</l>
                  <l>Wo worth (may our great <hi>Pan,</hi> and we his Puples say) that Frier,</l>
                  <l>That by reuealing Christ obscur'd to Christ did Soules retire.</l>
                  <l>For since great <hi>Pans</hi> great Vicar on the Earth was disobaid</l>
                  <l>In <hi>England,</hi> I beyond the Seas a Mal-Content haue staid.</l>
                  <l>Whence, by a brute of Pouder that should blow to heauen or hell</l>
                  <pb n="368" facs="tcp:20257:20"/>
                  <l> The Protestants, I hither came, where all I found too well:</l>
                  <l>And in the <hi>Catholick</hi> maine Cause small hope, or rather none:</l>
                  <l>No sooner therefore was I come but that I wisht me gone.</l>
                  <l>Was then a merrie world with vs when <hi>Mary</hi> wore the Crowne,</l>
                  <l>And holy-water-sprinkle was beleeud to put vs downe.</l>
                  <l>Ho ho ho ho, needs must I laugh such fooleries to name:</l>
                  <l>And at my crummed messe of Milke each night, frō Maid or Dame</l>
                  <l>To do their chares, as they supposd, when in their deadest sleepe</l>
                  <l>I puld them out their beds, &amp; made themselues their houses sweepe.</l>
                  <l>How clatterd I amongst their Pots and Pans, as dreamed they?</l>
                  <l>My Hempen Hampen Sentence, whē some tender foole would lay</l>
                  <l>Me shirt or slop, them greeued, for I then would go away.</l>
                  <l>Yee <hi>Fairies</hi> too made Mothers, if weake faith, to sweare that ye</l>
                  <l>Into their Beds did foist your Babes, and theirs exchang'd to be.</l>
                  <l>When yee (that eluish Manners did from eluish Shapes obserue)</l>
                  <l>By pinching her that beat that child, made Child &amp; Mother swerue,</l>
                  <l>This in that erd beliefe, That, not corrected, bad that grew:</l>
                  <l>Thus yee, I, Pope, and Cloysterers all in one Teame then drew.</l>
                  <l>But all things haue gone crosse with vs since here the Gospell shind,</l>
                  <l>Nor helps it aught that She that it vnclowded is inshrind.</l>
                  <l>Well, though our <hi>Romish</hi> Exorcists and Regulars be outed,</l>
                  <l>No lesse Hypocrisie mongst some their Contraries is doubted:</l>
                  <l>And may they so perseuer and so perish <hi>Robin</hi> prayes:</l>
                  <l>But too too zealous people are too many cloy my wayes.</l>
                  <l>For that this Realme is in the Right, <hi>Rome</hi> in the wrong for Loore</l>
                  <l>I must confesse, though much is else as faultie as before.</l>
                  <l>To Farmers came I, that, at least, their Lofe and Cheese once freed</l>
                  <l>For all would eate, but found themselues the parings now to need:</l>
                  <l>So do their Lādlords rack their Rents: though in the Mannor-Place</l>
                  <l>Scarce smoakt a Chimney: yet did Smoke perplex me in strāge cace.</l>
                  <l>I saw the Chimneys cleerd of fire, where nerethelesse it smokt</l>
                  <l>So bitterly, as one not vsed to like, it might haue chokt.</l>
                  <l>But when I saw it did proceed from Nostrels, and from Throtes</l>
                  <pb n="369" facs="tcp:20257:20"/>
                  <l> Of Ladies, Lords, and sillie Groomes, not burning skins nor Cotes,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Belsabub,</hi> thought I, can all spit fier as well as Thine?</l>
                  <l>Or where am I? it cannot be vnder the torred Line.</l>
                  <l>My fellow <hi>Incubus</hi> (who heere still Residence did keepe,</l>
                  <l>Witnes so many dadlesse Babes begot on Girles asleepe)</l>
                  <l>Did put me by that feare, and said it was an <hi>Indian</hi> weede,</l>
                  <l>That feum'd away more wealth than would a many thousands feed.</l>
                  <l>Freed of that feare, the noueltie of Cooches scath'd me so,</l>
                  <l>As from their drifts and cluttering I knew not where to go.</l>
                  <l>These also worke, quoth <hi>Incubus,</hi> to our auaile, for why?</l>
                  <l>They tend to idle Pride, and to Inhospitalitie.</l>
                  <l>With that I, comforted, did then peepe into euery one,</l>
                  <l>And of mine old acquaintances spide many a countrie Ione,</l>
                  <l>Whose fathers droue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Dung-cart, though the daughters now will.</l>
                  <l>I knew whē Prelates, &amp; the Peeres had faire attendance on none.</l>
                  <l>By Gentlemen and Yeomandrie, but that faire world is gone:</l>
                  <l>For most, like <hi>Iehu,</hi> hurrie with Pedanties two or three,</l>
                  <l>Yet all go downe the winde, saue those that hospitalious bee.</l>
                  <l>Great'st Ladies with their women, on their Palfries mounted faire,</l>
                  <l>Rode through the streets, well waited on, their artlesse faces bare,</l>
                  <l>Which now in Coches scorne to be salued of the aire.</l>
                  <l>I knew when men-Iudiciall rode on sober Mules, whereby</l>
                  <l>They might of Suters, these, and they aske, Answere, and Replie.</l>
                  <l>I knew when more was thriu'd abroad by war than now by peace,</l>
                  <l>And English feard where they be frumpt, since hostile tearmes did cease:</l>
                  <l>But by Occasion, all things are produced, be, decrease.</l>
                  <l>Times were whē Practize also preacht, and well said was well-done,</l>
                  <l>When Courtiors cleerd the old before they on the new would run,</l>
                  <l>When no iudiciall place was bought, lest Iustice might be sould,</l>
                  <l>When Quirts, nor Quillets ouerthrew, or long did Causes hold,</l>
                  <l>When Lawyers more deserud their fees, &amp; fatted lesse with gold.</l>
                  <l>When to the fifteenth Psalme, sometimes, had Citizens recourse,</l>
                  <l>When Lords of Farmers, Farmers of the poore had more remorse.</l>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="chapter">
               <pb n="372" facs="tcp:20257:21"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>No sooner ioyne the Battels but the <hi>Saxons</hi> them withdrew,</l>
                  <l>And neutrally from hils aloofe the Execution view.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Picts</hi> so weakened, <hi>Donskene</hi> yet from <hi>Donskene</hi> no whit swarues,</l>
                  <l>But still a dauntlesse heart vnto a dismall houre resarues:</l>
                  <l>And what a complet Captaine might in nothing did omit,</l>
                  <l>Incountring and incouraging, when, where, and what was fit:</l>
                  <l>Nor their innatiue Prowesse did his People then forgit:</l>
                  <l>Nor Field was euer fought with more perseuerant Swords than it.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> (to whom all <hi>Britaine</hi> in times Reuolutions was</l>
                  <l>Inaugurated) did their Maine at fearelesse hazard pas:</l>
                  <l>Whilst <hi>Picts,</hi> that should vnpeople now, as fruit vnripened fell:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Scots</hi> at least with <hi>Picts</hi> alike might slaughtred Corpses tell.</l>
                  <l>Seauen times that fatall day the <hi>Picts</hi> renewed fight in vaine,</l>
                  <l>Till almost all did perish, and their valiant King was slaine:</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Donskene</hi> so vnto the <hi>Picts</hi> both ended Realme and Raigne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Camelon</hi> (now in rubble, then a spatious Citie strong,</l>
                  <l>Wherein the Romaine Presidents had hild their States of long,</l>
                  <l>Nor could for bewtifull this Isle boast like, else books be wrong,</l>
                  <l>Though hardly now (as <hi>Verelon)</hi> it Ruins found among)</l>
                  <l>Held Pictish yet: to which those few that had escaped flead,</l>
                  <l>Beseeged now: the which to race, and all therein for dead</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> had vowed. Whereupon such despret Sallies bread,</l>
                  <l>That, had not hate in <hi>scottish</hi> hearts bread <hi>Lethargie</hi> of feare,</l>
                  <l>Their Obstinacie had giuen place to dreadfull Obiects theare.</l>
                  <l>But losse nor labour <hi>Kenneth</hi> cares whereby the <hi>Picts</hi> might fall:</l>
                  <l>Whilst these esteemd incessant toyles and greatest dangers small.</l>
                  <l>When long, and to the <hi>Scots</hi> themselues the Siege had lossefull bin,</l>
                  <l>(For <hi>Picts</hi> had vowed not to loose, as <hi>Scots</hi> the Towne to win)</l>
                  <l>And that such famine had inrag'd within the walles, so sore,</l>
                  <l>As that they were inforst to eate what Nature did abhore,</l>
                  <l>By Stratagemes effecting was at last the Citie lost:</l>
                  <l>In winning which alternallie it ouer-dearely cost.</l>
                  <l>But Victors were the <hi>Scots,</hi> that spar'd nor Priest, nor Sexe, nor age,</l>
                  <pb n="373" facs="tcp:20257:21"/>
                  <l> But slaughter all, and quite race downe <hi>Camelon</hi> in their rage.</l>
                  <l>Thus, after twise sixe hundred yeares, this Citie and that State</l>
                  <l>Were cleane extirpt, through <hi>Scots,</hi> thereto ordaind by shiftlesse fate.</l>
                  <l>Who also wrought in all, so farre as then in them did lye,</l>
                  <l>That euen the very name of <hi>Picts</hi> to future times should dye.</l>
                  <l>But neither Swords, nor fir'd Records, nor alterd names of all,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Enuies-</hi>selfe, this of their worth extinguish, hope we shall.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="book">
            <head>THE FIFTEENTH BOOKE <hi>OF ALBIONS ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="93" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 93.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Scots</hi> thus conquerd <hi>Penthland,</hi> when two Nations more remaind</l>
                  <l>Within this Iland, also to their Empire pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordaind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britons</hi> (now <hi>Welsh)</hi> and <hi>Saxons</hi> (now cald <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish)</hi> either twaine</l>
                  <l>From then a world of time remote vnited to their Raigne:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Ireland</hi> also (whence they were) in <hi>Englands</hi> right they gaine.</l>
                  <l>But by what Currants resteth now in breuitie to say,</l>
                  <l>More facle, by how much the more I see that wished day</l>
                  <l>Of all by-passed ages now effected fully in</l>
                  <l>His Maiestie, that Monarchie doth of this Ile begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="374" facs="tcp:20257:22"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Picts</hi> thus past, more of the <hi>Scots</hi> shall be remembred, when</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Welsh,</hi> more aunchant <hi>Incolants,</hi> distaske our willing pen.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Welsh</hi> and <hi>Scots,</hi> so far-forth we <hi>Aborigens</hi> may name,</l>
                  <l>As that they held them heere intier since first they hither came.</l>
                  <l>We Modernes are compounded of them both, <hi>Picts, Romaines,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Armoricanes, Danes, Normaines,</hi> all once breeding in this land.</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Brittish, English, Scottish,</hi> and the <hi>Danish</hi> bloods vnite</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Englands</hi> royall Issue now, what wrongs haue they to right?</l>
                  <l>But that, for Consanguinitie, we may, coleaug'd with those,</l>
                  <l>God set before, set dread behinde of whatsoeuer foes.</l>
                  <l>May all their virtues grifted in our Natures shew euents</l>
                  <l>In this our <hi>Eden</hi> worthy still at least of such discents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> heere preuailing, latenlie, old <hi>Britons, Picts,</hi> were said,</l>
                  <l>Of their self-painting, whēce foe-feard they did thēselues perswaid.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> outed, <hi>Pictish Britons</hi> did <hi>Brittish</hi> Reuolts inuaid,</l>
                  <l>Because those Lattres (basely thought those Formers) <hi>Rome</hi> obaid:</l>
                  <l>For these though seuerd earst were one. Then <hi>Scots</hi> extirpt the <hi>Picts:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then came the <hi>Saxons,</hi> and to <hi>Wales</hi> debelled <hi>Brutes</hi> Relicts:</l>
                  <l>Where yet they are a People, and had there their natiue Kings,</l>
                  <l>And in that war-saud Countrie in their Countrie, acted things</l>
                  <l>Whereof (their insufficient <hi>Bard)</hi> my Muse too skantie sings.</l>
                  <l>At last to th'<hi>englisht Normaine</hi> yoke them ciuell discord brings.</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Britons (saxonlie</hi> cald <hi>Welsh,</hi> or Strangers) touch we heere</l>
                  <l>Occurrents, as in weale or woe the same concernd them neere:</l>
                  <l>Yea progresse we awhile through <hi>Wales,</hi> where <hi>Brute</hi> his off-springs seed,</l>
                  <l>Vnder their natiue Princes long did many a glorious deed:</l>
                  <l>And that those <hi>Britons</hi> braue Remaines time frō tumultuous brings,</l>
                  <l>Was not our Armor, but our late Alacritie of Kings.</l>
                  <l>For, since protected in same Lawes, and mixt with vs in blood,</l>
                  <l>Bad Brookers they of violence prou'd Voluntaries good,</l>
                  <l>And to themselues haue happy, to our State haue loyall stood.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cadwalader,</hi> as is before, transfreated, forst thereto</l>
                  <l>By what th'inuading <hi>Saxons</hi> and the Pestilence did do,</l>
                  <pb n="375" facs="tcp:20257:22"/>
                  <l> The Things of <hi>Wales,</hi> as <hi>Saxons</hi> too, confusedly did stand:</l>
                  <l>The cause Pluralitie of Kings aduanst in either land.</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Saxons</hi> did in <hi>Lhoyger</hi> (so the <hi>Welsh</hi> cald <hi>England)</hi> chuse</l>
                  <l>(Which honor thence West<hi>-Saxon</hi> Kings in that <hi>Heptarchia</hi> vse)</l>
                  <l>A souereigne Generall for their warres against their cōmon foes,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Brittish-Cambries (Welsh men</hi> now) a like Superior choes,</l>
                  <l>Twixt which <hi>Alienigenests</hi> not sildome warfare groes.</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Rodericke,</hi> surnamd the great, did monarchize at last</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wales,</hi> that had neere as many Kings as <hi>Cantreses</hi> in times past,</l>
                  <l>Reducing all to three, whereof were Tributaries twaine</l>
                  <l>Vnto the third, North<hi>-Wales,</hi> which thence did Paramount remaine.</l>
                  <l>Of North<hi>-Wales,</hi> South<hi>-Wales, Powys-</hi>land, making bequests he dide,</l>
                  <l>And his three Sonnes those Diuidents in Thrones distinct supplide.</l>
                  <l>Of all things there, long out of ioint, in order as they fell</l>
                  <l>Through vsurpations, ciuill warres, and <hi>Danes</hi> were long to tell,</l>
                  <l>But of those indigested daies this merits obseruation,</l>
                  <l>At ods they euend against Aliēts, nor mixt bloud with forren natiō.</l>
                  <l>Yet, though against the <hi>Welsh-</hi>Kings will, our royall Surname now</l>
                  <l>(If Historie therein we may authenticall allow)</l>
                  <l>It Seedster from that kingly Streene deriues, ensueth how.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 94.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ne <hi>Makebeth,</hi> who had traitrously his sometimes Souereigne slaine,</l>
                  <l>And like a Monster not a Man vsurpt in <hi>Scotland</hi> raigne,</l>
                  <l>Whose guiltie Conscience did it selfe so feelingly accuse,</l>
                  <l>As nothing not applide by him against himselfe he vewes,</l>
                  <pb n="376" facs="tcp:20257:23"/>
                  <l> No whispring but of him, gainst him all weapons feares he borne,</l>
                  <l>All Beings iointly to reuenge his Murthres thinks he sworne,</l>
                  <l>Wherefore (for such are euer such in selfe-tormenting mind)</l>
                  <l>But to proceed in bloud he thought no saferie to find.</l>
                  <l>All Greatnesse therefore, saue his owne his, driftings did infest:</l>
                  <l>Wit so is wisedomes Excrement, and dangerously transgrest.</l>
                  <l>But Pomp, nor Policie, the poore in spirit shall be blest,</l>
                  <l>When at the generall Doome our Soules and Sathan shall contest.</l>
                  <l>One <hi>Banquho,</hi> powrefulst of the Peers, in popular affection</l>
                  <l>And prowesse great, was murthred by his tyrannous direction.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fleance</hi> therefore this <hi>Banquhos</hi> sonne fled thence to <hi>Wales</hi> for feare,</l>
                  <l>Whome <hi>Gruffyth</hi> kindly did receiue, and cherisht nobly there.</l>
                  <l>This grew so rare in Court, as him did euery Eie and Eare</l>
                  <l>Desier to see for person, for discourse delight to heare.</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Gruffyths</hi> Daughter, Paragon for bewtie and for wit,</l>
                  <l>He followed with such Offices to complet Courtship fit,</l>
                  <l>That each to other sympathiz'd such setled liking, as</l>
                  <l>Her heart to his, his heart to hers transplantiuely did passe.</l>
                  <l>In other Courts for either Sexe not amorous to appeare</l>
                  <l>Was not to be a Courtior, but such boldnesse faulted theare:</l>
                  <l>Her lou'd of him, him lou'd of her, was patent to them both,</l>
                  <l>Yet dombly so, and either that should th'other noote it loth.</l>
                  <l>Not he, by Sonnets passonate, did giue the world to wit</l>
                  <l>That he was turnd <hi>Hermaphrodit,</hi> and she the cause of it:</l>
                  <l>Nor borrowed she of <hi>Phaos</hi> box thereby to seeme more faire,</l>
                  <l>As those that fondly rob themselues by Arte of that they are.</l>
                  <l>Through this occasion lassly thus he nakt to her his heart:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I pree thee, <hi>Fleance,</hi> tell quoth she, which I haue heard in part,</l>
                  <l>The Storie of <hi>Fairies</hi> that foretold thy Fathers fate,</l>
                  <l>For why? I know not why, but sure it throbs my heart of late.</l>
                  <l>Throb may it so it thriue, quoth he, in you to that euent</l>
                  <l>Diuind by them, nor hope I you can Destinie preuent:</l>
                  <l>But howsoeuer thus it was. King <hi>Duncane</hi> when aliue,</l>
                  <pb n="377" facs="tcp:20257:23"/>
                  <l> To <hi>Makbeth</hi> and my father did great Dignities deriue,</l>
                  <l>As chiefest for their births, their wit, and valour, also thay</l>
                  <l>Held friendship long, and luckely in <hi>Scotch</hi> affaires did sway.</l>
                  <l>Three <hi>Fairies</hi> in a priuate walke to them appeared, who</l>
                  <l>Saluted <hi>Makbeth</hi> King, and gaue him other Titles too:</l>
                  <l>To whom my father, laughing, said they dealt vnequall dole,</l>
                  <l>Behighting nought thereof to him, but to his Friend the whole.</l>
                  <l>When of the <hi>Weird-Elfes</hi> one of them, replying, said that he</l>
                  <l>Should not be King, but of his Streene a many Kings should be.</l>
                  <l>So vanish they: and what they said of <hi>Makbeth</hi> now we see.</l>
                  <l>But murdred is my father, and of him remaines but me,</l>
                  <l>Nor shall what they diuin'd effect, vnlesse, sweet Sweet, by thee.</l>
                  <l>What blush you, Lady, pree thee let me busse that blush away,</l>
                  <l>He said, and did it, She to seeke euen of a womans Nay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Louers opportunely meet to chaffer fire and flaxe,</l>
                  <l>Will somtimes falles too soone a worke, and Wit thereof doth taxe:</l>
                  <l>This amourous Couples close Cōtract perform'd such earnest sport,</l>
                  <l>As worser newes than would their tongues her belly did report.</l>
                  <l>The fault apparant, <hi>Fleance</hi> was by furious <hi>Gruffyth</hi> kild,</l>
                  <l>And she, deliuered of a Sonne, was in affliction hild.</l>
                  <l>The rather for an Aliant had preuailed in that case,</l>
                  <l>Than which amongst the <hi>Welsh-men</hi> thē was nothing more disgrace.</l>
                  <l>And, soothly, vnto these our times in <hi>Europe</hi> scarce is knowne</l>
                  <l>As North<hi>-Wales</hi> is, a Nation more intirely People-one,</l>
                  <l>But that so long in one same Land haue hild them thinke I none,</l>
                  <l>If be not naturall <hi>Irish</hi> for abode and Breede out-worne.</l>
                  <l>From these so haplesse Parents yeat an happie Sonne proceeded,</l>
                  <l>Well educated of the King, and prouing nobly deeded,</l>
                  <l>At age admir'd for actiue, and for high imployments apt:</l>
                  <l>But for the vertuous to haue bin enuied euer hapt.</l>
                  <l>One taxing him of Bastardie, words more than he could brooke,</l>
                  <l>Was slaine by him: who fearing Law his flight to <hi>Scotland</hi> tooke.</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Walter</hi> (for it was his name) exact of noble blood,</l>
                  <pb n="378" facs="tcp:20257:24"/>
                  <l> And Grand-sonne to the King of <hi>Wales,</hi> in publique fauour stood.</l>
                  <l>Amongst great honors, which his great Achiuemēts well did merit,</l>
                  <l>He was Lord <hi>Steward</hi> of the Land: which Sur-name all inherit</l>
                  <l>Of him descended to this day: which Surname, and which Streene</l>
                  <l>Hath blest the <hi>Scots</hi> with Princes eight, Ours also numbers neene:</l>
                  <l>Great Monarke of great <hi>Britaine</hi> now, so amply neuer any:</l>
                  <l>Long may he liue an happie King, of him may Kings be many.</l>
                  <l>Boast of his triple royall blood from you yee <hi>Cambrian Brutes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which to his high discents Else-where not lowest ranked sutes.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Tudor</hi> from <hi>Cadwallader,</hi> and <hi>Iames</hi> from <hi>Tudor</hi> claimes,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Gruffyths</hi> royall Daughter too himselfe a <hi>Brute</hi> he names,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Gladys, Mortimer</hi> his wife Prince <hi>Dauids</hi> sister and</l>
                  <l>Vndoubted heire, he also hath in blood and ownes your Land.</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> sith a <hi>Briton</hi> doth remonarchize thy Throne,</l>
                  <l>Remaūd thy name: <hi>Brute</hi> had, <hi>Iames</hi> hath the whole, as els had none.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What then remaines, sith all is Ones, but all be one in all,</l>
                  <l>And Schismes be reconcilde or scourg'd, for God quaints not with <hi>Baal.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The great Surname of <hi>Steward,</hi> how it royaliz'd shall rest</l>
                  <l>For amplier Storie, and of <hi>Wales</hi> shall be awhile digrest.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 95.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ay me, of gadding, whispring, and of reall Papists, who</l>
                  <l>Wish not that <hi>Romes Palladium</hi> might as <hi>Greekes</hi> to <hi>Troy</hi> Here doe?</l>
                  <l>Nay, which of most the Popes their deeds, in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratie, did touch</l>
                  <l>Of these vsurped <hi>Sur-names</hi> (Names purporting vertue much)</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Clement, Pius, Benedict,</hi> with <hi>Boniface,</hi> and such?</l>
                  <pb n="379" facs="tcp:20257:24"/>
                  <l> The Contrary in these and their blind Dogmatists is true:</l>
                  <l>Witnes <hi>Guy Faux</hi> his god-curst Taske set by a Pope-blist Crew.</l>
                  <l>But thy Name, <hi>Faux,</hi> apts Latinlie vnto thy Nature bad:</l>
                  <l>Saue pitie more euen Tigers iawes haue than thy blood-thirst had.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France, Belgick, Spaine, Cis-Trans-Alpine,</hi> had they against vs arm'd,</l>
                  <l>All they in this vnited Isle had (if at all) lesse harm'd,</l>
                  <l>(For euen a Conquest, though it much addes, alters, and ablates,</l>
                  <l>To, in, and from, a vassald State, not howbeit vn-States)</l>
                  <l>Than this one Viper in his Denne, by one vnthought of blow,</l>
                  <l>Hels stratagemous Quintessence, <hi>Romes</hi> selfe-created Foe:</l>
                  <l>For henceforth who, not senselesse, to her Oracle will goe?</l>
                  <l>Those all, I say; yea all the worlds ioynt Armour neuer had,</l>
                  <l>Or could they would they barbarously haue bin so ruthlesse bad,</l>
                  <l>As in a trice had been perform'd by <hi>Faux,</hi> abetted by</l>
                  <l>Conspirators, more odious than their names to shame can dye.</l>
                  <l>Yea, but that Prouender them prickt, by some that might haue said,</l>
                  <l>Soule take thine Ease, here vp in store enough for thee is laid.</l>
                  <l>But Gold, I trow, would be a God it gathereth so of Stile:</l>
                  <l>To be a Noble, Soueraigne, nor an Angel, worth the while.</l>
                  <l>Like to which Climaxie of Coyne wealth eleuates the minde</l>
                  <l>To tract of Greatnesse, till mongst men be <hi>Lucifers</hi> declinde.</l>
                  <l>Besides a many Innocents, not aim'd at or remorsed,</l>
                  <l>His Maiesties, Queenes, Of-springs breathes from their sweet bodies forced,</l>
                  <l>The Prelacie, Nobilitie, States-men, and State betraide,</l>
                  <l>None to consult, none to commaund, obey, or be obeyde,</l>
                  <l>Protestants, Papists, Puritanes, and Atheists by the eares,</l>
                  <l>All in Confusion, Rapines, blood, in horror, Schismes, and feares,</l>
                  <l>How many vnprepared Soules in that one tragick Blast</l>
                  <l>Had, vnrepentant, what car'd <hi>Rome</hi> to whom or whither past?</l>
                  <l>That Parlament, that should haue blist an hopefull <hi>Vnion</hi> here</l>
                  <l>Twixt <hi>English</hi> and the <hi>Scots,</hi> had left nor <hi>Vnion,</hi> King, nor Peere,</l>
                  <l>Nor of the royall Impes, nor whom, but better had been dead</l>
                  <l>Than to haue seene those miseries that Massacre had bread:</l>
                  <l>A Massacre? nay vilder than affining Terme is read.</l>
                  <pb n="380" facs="tcp:20257:25"/>
                  <l> Nor had those Diuels themselues sped as their Proiect had decreed,</l>
                  <l>Whilst <hi>Britaine</hi> had a <hi>Chrishian,</hi> and that <hi>Christian</hi> blood to bleed:</l>
                  <l>Nor any (if no Papist) though <hi>Mahumatist,</hi> or <hi>Iew,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or morall <hi>Idolast</hi> had brookt such irreligious View,</l>
                  <l>Nor Forren State, or Potentate, the Pope respecting lesse</l>
                  <l>Than Gods law, lawes of Nature, and of Nations to transgresse:</l>
                  <l>Or, doubtlesse, had selfe-Butcherie amongst those Butchers bin,</l>
                  <l>Like Wolues in sharing Praies, so God abhors such bloodie sinne:</l>
                  <l>Through whō, themselues that dig'd for vs the Pit are falne therin.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes Neros-</hi>fire, <hi>Guyse-</hi>Massacre, <hi>Herods</hi> Act, <hi>Hamons</hi> Minde,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Iohn, French Henrie</hi> murdred, moe, nor any in that kinde,</l>
                  <l>Pagan, nor Popish Crueltie here Parallel can finde:</l>
                  <l>For blood and sower designes so farre beyond Example all,</l>
                  <l>As Children now, when they be men, beleeue it hardly shall.</l>
                  <l>Then, <hi>Britons,</hi> whē ye blesse your Babes, mixt may your blessings be</l>
                  <l>With this, that they take Caution that did <hi>Papisme</hi> thus decree:</l>
                  <l>Whence true Tradition of the Fruit may blanch thē frō the Tree.</l>
                  <l>Yea, let them listen, lothingly, what <hi>Iesuites</hi> propound</l>
                  <l>Gainst Kings &amp; States, perfidiously t'aduāce their Triple crownd:</l>
                  <l>For which, euen <hi>Atheisme</hi> (theirs except) disclaimeth any ground.</l>
                  <l>Yet out of Practise, Purpose, Terme, and None it to relate</l>
                  <l>May be that diulish Doctrine whence they now <hi>Equiuocate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For we may vouch our Age to haue begotten two such Twinnes,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Manual</hi> meant, This <hi>Mental</hi> brocht, as comprehend all Sinnes.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Gangrens</hi> as Decision fits (the sooner better) so</l>
                  <l>This Latters Breath choake at its Birth, that else wil monstrous grow.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Hercules</hi> was preacht a God to so Beleeuers, it</l>
                  <l>Was taxt a needlesse Doctrine: But this Loore▪Strife more vnfit,</l>
                  <l>Sith <hi>Romes Amphibologie</hi> faults to Trust, Religion, wit:</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Paganisme,</hi> yea <hi>Atheisme</hi> hist, deriued from <hi>Hels</hi> Pit.</l>
                  <l>The fabled <hi>Satyre</hi> came to dine, but when his hoste for Colde</l>
                  <l>Did blow his Nayles, his Pottage too for heate, not stay he would,</l>
                  <l>Disparitie from one same Breath, him scathed to behould.</l>
                  <l>Tongues-Othes, Harts-Thoughts, Disiūctiues, by a <hi>Mētal</hi> reseruatiō,</l>
                  <pb n="381" facs="tcp:20257:25"/>
                  <l> What Lawes, whose life or State secure, should such not be <hi>Nugation?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such cannot be of God, therefore it selfe cannot but kill,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>trulie falslie</hi> sworne doth sinne, yea <hi>Good</hi> that tracts of <hi>Ill.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No Beasts, of whom but selfe-Repose to be disturbd is feard,</l>
                  <l>Will suffer that amongst them this bigenderd Beast shall heard.</l>
                  <l>Absurdities vncontrouerst, as silenst then let goe:</l>
                  <l>It prouds a <hi>Schismatick</hi> when him disputes a learned foe.</l>
                  <l>But, Infants-now, by yee be men, or might if ye shall liue,</l>
                  <l>An vniuersall Hate is hopte to <hi>Rome</hi> an End shall giue:</l>
                  <l>Hate? and an End right iusticed against that purple Whore:</l>
                  <l>My soule for yours, if hers you hate, and shall imbrace our Lore.</l>
                  <l>Wise is he that spake wisely thus the veritie in this,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Mysterie</hi> of <hi>Iniquitie</hi> in perfect <hi>Papisme</hi> is.</l>
                  <l>Amongst a many Instancies, the vgliest was this Plot,</l>
                  <l>Preuented earst miraculously: nor be the meanes forgot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mount-Eagle</hi> (than that Names-birth, Gods preordinance more Strange</l>
                  <l>In that darkt loue, meant sole to thee, such Prodigies should change)</l>
                  <l>Mount Eagle thine as high a pitch as Prince-bird of thy kinde</l>
                  <l>Did euer, and thy loyaltie liue in the Lions minde:</l>
                  <l>Whose great-grand-Mothers Father too, Birds of thy feather foūd</l>
                  <l>That, chiefly, thrown'd him in his Right, a Tyrāt then dis-crownd,</l>
                  <l>For which, long ciuil warres so ceast, and this, should al confound,</l>
                  <l>But God vsde thee a counter-meanes, rests <hi>England</hi> deeply bound</l>
                  <l>To theirs and thine auspitious Bird, still to its Scepter sound.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="chapter">
               <pb n="382" facs="tcp:20257:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 96.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onsult thy selfe, dread Soueraigne, and thy Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, how may</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Romish Hydras</hi> heads be seard, or Monster ridde away.</l>
                  <l>For sith they doome all Heretiks not suting to their Lore,</l>
                  <l>And faith with vs not to be held, but foehood euermore,</l>
                  <l>And sith for Murthers Merits, Othes Remissiō, heauē for Treason,</l>
                  <l>Hath their Religion them to doubt, that all things dare, is reason:</l>
                  <l>But God it is that broke the Snare, watch, pray we euery Season.</l>
                  <l>And, as thy Courtiers, also let thy Commons, sacred King,</l>
                  <l>Vnto thine affabilitie and bountie <hi>Poeans</hi> sing.</l>
                  <l>Than which, is thought, that nothing more assures a Regall-Seate,</l>
                  <l>Which seeming silly do, vndone, much Scathe to Scepters threate:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> most sweet wert thou, in each heart-chayning feate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And miserable Papists, too delirously mislead,</l>
                  <l>To whom are Othes, blood, what not Hels, may stand your Sect in stead?</l>
                  <l>Indulgenced, Only to you, and only are forbod</l>
                  <l>The Scriptures and our Churches, lest yee turne from Pope to God.</l>
                  <l>O, rather take the warrantize of that sole Deitie</l>
                  <l>That, bidding search the Scriptures, saith of him they testifie.</l>
                  <l>Peruse them yet, frequent our Church, confer with our Diuines:</l>
                  <l>So shall ye finde <hi>Rome</hi> false, and lesse to care your faith than fines:</l>
                  <l>For to the Centure of selfe-Pompe directeth all her Lines:</l>
                  <l>Nor can it be Religion that so diuelishly designes:</l>
                  <l>As did your late preuented Plot, that <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell combines.</l>
                  <l>For all yet said, is nothing to that more that might be said,</l>
                  <l>Of our compleatest Parlament that should haue been betraid:</l>
                  <pb n="383" facs="tcp:20257:26"/>
                  <l> And new <hi>Rome,</hi> that for Infamie too long hath famous bin,</l>
                  <l>Vncontradicted, for that Plot from Hell the Palme doth win.</l>
                  <l>Sith <hi>Peters-</hi>selfe, first Patriarke in your Church, as yee pretend,</l>
                  <l>Was taught, and taught, meeknesse and Loue, so liu'd, and so did end,</l>
                  <l>Sith thirtie three succeeding in that Chaire were martyrd such,</l>
                  <l>And all the Fathers There (of Stile no higher would they touch)</l>
                  <l>Were abiect poore, till <hi>Constantine</hi> inritched them too much,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Phocas</hi> for his Priuats <hi>Rome</hi> the Supreme Sea promoted,</l>
                  <l>How is it of Supremacie, as if from <hi>Christ,</hi> then doted?</l>
                  <l>Well, if in Church-affaires ye in your Follies so admit,</l>
                  <l>Yet that be Popes Heauens Porters, or the Gaylers of Hels Pit,</l>
                  <l>Or that their <hi>Mittimus</hi> to This, <hi>Admittimus</hi> to That,</l>
                  <l>Be worth a farthing of the Price, creed they that care not what.</l>
                  <l>But certis, Papistrie, that in it selfe is so absurd,</l>
                  <l>Of learned men and Princes, that conferre it with Gods word,</l>
                  <l>Is vsde but for selfe-purposes and Policies a Staile,</l>
                  <l>And whither will the head we know that thither will the Taile.</l>
                  <l>What Warres, Inuasions, Rebels, Plots, at least since <hi>Luthers</hi> daies,</l>
                  <l>But thence had hopes, Buls, or Pretexts, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Maine meant other waies.</l>
                  <l>How many Kings for Coyne-cause, or repelling but Pope-pride,</l>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Rome</hi> infested, though with her the same in all beside?</l>
                  <l>Most-what by Women, sillie Girles, youths, firie-wits, Ambitious,</l>
                  <l>By great, by needy Mal-Contents, by Credulous, and Vitious,</l>
                  <l>Work <hi>Romes</hi> Committees, &amp; from flesh to fare much more delicious</l>
                  <l>Penance their Puples: whitest Sons these Seedsters and Seditious.</l>
                  <l>And, that for them libentiously Fooles-Catholike should erre,</l>
                  <l>Pensions, Canonizing at least, on <hi>Rome-</hi>wrights they conferre.</l>
                  <l>But, if had spead their barbarous Plot of vaulted Powder late,</l>
                  <l>Then friends and foes, vncarde of them, had past in one same rate,</l>
                  <l>And Agents too: Religion was the bye, the Maine the State.</l>
                  <l>Deluded Soules, in only Christ ground all Faith, Loue, and Hope;</l>
                  <l>A mortall Man, sinfull as ye, or worser is the Pope,</l>
                  <l>Your Coyne of all his Practises and Pedlaries the scope.</l>
                  <pb n="384" facs="tcp:20257:27"/>
                  <l> So violently, blasphemously, and suddainly haue dide</l>
                  <l>So many Popes, as in no Ranke of States hath hapt beside.</l>
                  <l>And to vsurpe the <hi>Papacie,</hi> such treacherous Intrusions,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Romes</hi> Religion, and her Rites, such false and harsh Conclusions,</l>
                  <l>Such Simonie, Pride, Briberie, and Brothelrie is There,</l>
                  <l>Yea and <hi>Sodometrie,</hi> as not exampled are Els-where.</l>
                  <l>Such is your God, his Oracle, his Orgies, and his Alter,</l>
                  <l>O venture not your Soules for such, to heuen-wards through an halter.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Babel</hi> is falne, <hi>Vr-Caldick</hi> squencht, <hi>Delphos</hi> in no request,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pantheon</hi> none for <hi>Ethnick</hi> Gods, <hi>Iewdaisme</hi> finds no rest,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mahumetrie</hi> hath but it time, the <hi>Arian</hi> and old store</l>
                  <l>Of Heresies are silenced, hath <hi>Romes</hi> then Placcard more?</l>
                  <l>Nay, let her looke a full Eclipse of her aie darkned Moone,</l>
                  <l>By interponure of the Sunne that shall vnshine it soone.</l>
                  <l>And (which is read as holy writ) the Legend of their Saints</l>
                  <l>To wisemens View, vpon that Pale <hi>Anathema</hi> it paints.</l>
                  <l>The Statute in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> raigne, when <hi>Poole</hi> re<hi>-Rom'd</hi> this Realme,</l>
                  <l>Doth arrogate vnto that Sea in tearmes too much extreame.</l>
                  <l>Yet some for selfe-Preferments, some to please, in blindnes moste,</l>
                  <l>Or how soeuer, wrought it was that <hi>Rome</hi> did rule the Roste.</l>
                  <l>But this be noted, worth the note, though <hi>Rome</hi> then soules re-got,</l>
                  <l>The Abbie-Lands, though labouring it, she reposseeded not:</l>
                  <l>Her trusted they with those, themselues with these, &amp; quasht had bin</l>
                  <l>That holie Statute, rather than a Land-saue not put in.</l>
                  <l>The pride of that same Prelacie, far lesse than since and now,</l>
                  <l>Euen in a Saint of theirs did our old Christians disalow,</l>
                  <l>Concerning which ensueth here, the Storie when and how.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="chapter">
               <pb n="385" facs="tcp:20257:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 97.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O <hi>Austin,</hi> first of <hi>Kentish</hi> Saints, doe lend your eares a while:</l>
                  <l>Not to his Legend (so absurd as, reade, would make yee smile,</l>
                  <l>Or rather good men grieue that stuffe so grosse should men beguile)</l>
                  <l>But of that Saint, whom <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Pope sent to this Isle,</l>
                  <l>So mou'd by feature that at <hi>Rome</hi> he saw in <hi>Englishmen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or Pagan <hi>Saxones,</hi> newly cal'd by name of <hi>English</hi> then.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Note, diuers hundred yeeres before that <hi>Lucius</hi> here was King,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Britons</hi> had receiu'd the faith, and though did Saxons bring</l>
                  <l>Hither with them their Paganisme and Christians did oppresse,</l>
                  <l>Amongst the then <hi>Welsh-Britons</hi> was the Gospell nerethelesse,</l>
                  <l>And Primatiue Church-Practise of trew Faith, for why? as yet</l>
                  <l>From Popes was no corruption brought, nor any from them fet.</l>
                  <l>But as their first Apostle, from Christs first Apostles, brought</l>
                  <l>Immediat Christianitie, at <hi>Bangor</hi> was it taught</l>
                  <l>Sincerely so, aboue those Clerkes till Primacie was sought</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Austin,</hi> then <hi>Romes</hi> Agent, fam'd such wonders to haue wrought,</l>
                  <l>As, if his Legend be no Lie (to deeme the best we ought)</l>
                  <l>Meere Exorcismes (for Miracles were ceast) they may be thought.</l>
                  <l>But sith not only Fathers in their bookes be falsefide,</l>
                  <l>But euen the sacred Scriptures, to vphold the Papall pride,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Austin</hi> and his fellow Saints may also be belide.</l>
                  <l>Of whom be reuerent Censure, that for most were men deuout,</l>
                  <l>Though in their Legends (others works) meere Fables are set out.</l>
               </lg>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="chapter">
               <pb n="388" facs="tcp:20257:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 98.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext these of Saints, vnsanctified, that also sturre the State,</l>
                  <l>Calumnize Church, our <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and Rites in criticke rate.</l>
                  <l>Yet (let not men religious, or but morall good replie)</l>
                  <l>What are they but the mapped Orbs of all Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie?</l>
                  <l>Of Humor, Pride, Peruersnesse fead, nor be Irreuerence spoke,</l>
                  <l>Too aduantagiously from out our <hi>Rubrick</hi> they vnyoke,</l>
                  <l>And Canons old and new by them are, too securely, broke,</l>
                  <l>Yea and, offensiuely, vnto our Regulars, submis</l>
                  <l>To meete Conformetie, that by Nouators dallied is.</l>
                  <l>For in euasiue Discipline, and tolerating Lawe,</l>
                  <l>Meant howsoeuer, baine from balme doe such Fantasticks drawe,</l>
                  <l>And giddie Flights of Bussards oft deuote them to some Dawe:</l>
                  <l>Who, howsoeuer he impungs our Order in Church Rites,</l>
                  <l>Them tearming <hi>Romish</hi> Ragges, or with his leaden Sword thē smites,</l>
                  <l>Yet whatsoeuer Papistrie exacted, payed yet,</l>
                  <l>His scrupulous Reformitie, will nought thereof remit.</l>
                  <l>Nay, Frier more did neuer preach deuotion to his Dame</l>
                  <l>Than these Addition, nor for aught with-hild did so exclame.</l>
                  <l>Which were indeed allowable in any more than These;</l>
                  <l>That are in all but for themselues, all would, will nothing leese.</l>
                  <l>Whose holy Noses ouer-hang at Markets, Staules, and Sacks,</l>
                  <l>There hucking cheapth, here hearkening dearth, to set abroach their Stacks.</l>
                  <l>And if of these Irregulars (as few haue) some giue-out,</l>
                  <pb n="389" facs="tcp:20257:28"/>
                  <l> They of their Owne prouided are sufficiently no doubt,</l>
                  <l>Or know to lay their knife aboord, at others Costs, for Fare</l>
                  <l>And greater Ease than Studie them or Pulpetrie can spare.</l>
                  <l>Or if shall of Pluralities be likely Risses, then</l>
                  <l>Their Saintships are as capable thereof as sinfull men.</l>
                  <l>Say somethings faultie in abuse of good Lawes, what of so?</l>
                  <l>A lawfull Calling, Season, Cause, still hand in hand should goe.</l>
                  <l>Synods &amp; Senats should they to preposterous Schismes giue place,</l>
                  <l>Lawes would be sick of Lunacie, still alter would the Cace.</l>
                  <l>The Adders Tayle, because it had the Sting, would hale the Head,</l>
                  <l>Ensewd, the blind Conductor to a deadly Down-fall lead.</l>
                  <l>Were Sailers scornd the Master for Director, him they drownd,</l>
                  <l>A Tempest hapt, none could direct, and all a Shipwrack found.</l>
                  <l>Of Plebales when they rush into Reformitie like ground,</l>
                  <l>And like successe: themselues for most cannot themselues expound.</l>
                  <l>Nor captiously be taine the Tearme of <hi>Puritane,</hi> but know,</l>
                  <l>To Puritie faind of Impure, so knowne, we badder owe,</l>
                  <l>Than by a bare <hi>Sarcasmus</hi> to obtrude on such the Lie</l>
                  <l>Of them beloued: Censure then of me as censure I,</l>
                  <l>That iterate, let Pharisies not Publicanes applie:</l>
                  <l>And care not Termes, but cleere the Schismes in peruerse humour lead,</l>
                  <l>And in a nick-nam'd Puritane an Hypocrite be read.</l>
                  <l>For vpright hearts, for holie hands, for reuerent tongues and eares</l>
                  <l>Be Scriptures only, and to God no secret but appeares.</l>
                  <l>Then babble lesse, and practise more of Pietie, if not,</l>
                  <l>By knowing good and doing ill the rather Hell is got.</l>
                  <l>Sith These and <hi>Romes,</hi> so dangerously, to Innouation tend</l>
                  <l>Against the Church and publike Peace, or breake or make thē bend:</l>
                  <l>At least, sith such <hi>Antitheses</hi> to Truth vnuisard are,</l>
                  <l>Yet selfe-accusing Consciences seducing not forbeare,</l>
                  <l>Of Spleene or Singularitie, no such Seducers spare.</l>
                  <l>Should Law lack force, or Iustice faint, as neither doth-or ought,</l>
                  <l>This comforts yet, Things not of God come of thēselues to nought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="390" facs="tcp:20257:29"/>
                  <l>Omitting serious Errants, and few pitied wits of some</l>
                  <l>Conceited, and exemplarly consorted, now though dumme,</l>
                  <l>Hopte howbeit no <hi>Lethargie</hi> their Senses doth benumme,</l>
                  <l>(For somtimes good men, till remou'd, to wrong Opinions leane)</l>
                  <l>Be medeld but of ayrie Saints, our Hypocrits we meane,</l>
                  <l>Of whom too many be obseru'd too subtile and vncleane.</l>
                  <l>Mongst many of an Hang-by in that kind, who, saue for gaine,</l>
                  <l>Sees Pulpets only, echoeth <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Magdalen</hi> doth faine,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>scriptum est,</hi> as did the Diuell, for her auaile applies,</l>
                  <l>Not for an Oxe an Oth, but for each trifle twentie Lies,</l>
                  <l>Tiers Catechizing, hangs at mouthes for scapes, when shall ye sware</l>
                  <l>Be'r-Lady or but Mack, for hot encounter then prepare,</l>
                  <l>Admireth others Faults, whilst she doth nothing more than worse,</l>
                  <l>Not sticking cautilously the hier of Filthinesse to purse,</l>
                  <l>For, may she opportune for Pence, liues not like lurching Blaine,</l>
                  <l>At her a cast, for now my Muse is in a merrie vaine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 99.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is an <hi>Academie,</hi> which I reuerence so much,</l>
                  <l>As gessed gainst it splenous thoughts me sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nously would touch:</l>
                  <l>For as (so Historie) it was the Primer-schooling Heere,</l>
                  <l>So euer haue Religion and the Muses held it deare:</l>
                  <l>What of Precisians? most retract, did Papists Else-where so,</l>
                  <l>Amisse were well amended: but too Wost-ward now we go.</l>
                  <l>Not miles from it a Township is, I know not whether in</l>
                  <pb n="391" facs="tcp:20257:29"/>
                  <l> A neighbouring Mart more famous, or infamous for the sinne</l>
                  <l>Of Beggers, Brothels, Cheaters, Bawds, and Vagrants once a yeere</l>
                  <l>Resorting thither, then to put their sinnes in practise there.</l>
                  <l>Farre be it though we taxe thereof those dwelling there, for why?</l>
                  <l>Proctors nor Praetors euer could those Of-scummes thence put by.</l>
                  <l>The harbouring then so fitting There, as those of Sort among</l>
                  <l>Are faine thereof. But all this while we doe our Hostesse wrong,</l>
                  <l>Who though she lack not of the age that Scriptures lot to man,</l>
                  <l>In auaritious Prouidence lesse Arte the Diuell can:</l>
                  <l>Her let vs Storie, as she swaies the Pot and dripping-pan.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So farre-foorth as her empted Goomes permitteth Guests she greets,</l>
                  <l>And promiseth to euery one soft lodging &amp; sweet sheets:</l>
                  <l>But who would thinke by misse of teeth y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> she with profit meets?</l>
                  <l>Full gorged mongst her Guests (for she with euery Company eates,</l>
                  <l>And slauers out some Decate of worme-eaten home-spun feates,</l>
                  <l>Or with her fellow Pharisies of Lecture-shreads intreates,</l>
                  <l>Or as she gropeth humours, so afferring stuffe repeates,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Proteu</hi> to all profit, hers as euery pulse so beates,</l>
                  <l>Well wotting now no thriuing if no hammering to all heates)</l>
                  <l>She, eating as chap-broken, of teeth-fugitiues complaines,</l>
                  <l>And for adiorned chewing so full fraughted trenchers gaines,</l>
                  <l>Which she retaileth: neither with that bootie so refraines,</l>
                  <l>But that some neighbour big with childe lusts this or that she faines,</l>
                  <l>And fourthly for her gulled Guests a galling shot remaines.</l>
                  <l>At table and in Stable when is frankly spent, and hopte</l>
                  <l>The promisd Lodging, no such thing, for many so gaine-coopt</l>
                  <l>Are glad, with fresh Expences for rear-banquets and great fiers,</l>
                  <l>All night to shelter bedlesse there: her selfe meane time retiers</l>
                  <l>To gnawed bones, and slubberd Scraps, and Trenchers, which she scrapes</l>
                  <l>So as no licking for a Mouse her frugall fingers scapes,</l>
                  <l>And with that sweet Compound condites such Gallimawfries as</l>
                  <l>She dearely vttereth to the Swaines that to and fro then pas.</l>
                  <pb n="392" facs="tcp:20257:30"/>
                  <l> Her parts externall more to praise, in sooth, I know not how,</l>
                  <l>Than that she eateth, grunts, and goes as clenly as a Sow,</l>
                  <l>Splay-footed, gated like a Beare, and wasted like a Cow,</l>
                  <l>And grease combust hides as a Maske her face of <hi>Baboon-</hi>forme.</l>
                  <l>Not wrothfull though, who so will may howsoeuer storme,</l>
                  <l>So she hath pay, that will be paid, if Bayard be in Stable,</l>
                  <l>And Bayard shall be there, for none she intertaines not able.</l>
                  <l>And though her wealth be great she hath no pride as may appeare,</l>
                  <l>So sluttish is her Wardrobe that she doth and doth not weare.</l>
                  <l>And he that at her Beauties best her kissed him repented,</l>
                  <l>Then Lecherie must needes in one so vgly be preuented.</l>
                  <l>She cannot be malitious doth with only Mony deale:</l>
                  <l>Nor enuious, vnto only whom Vertues themselues conceale.</l>
                  <l>And though that Gluttonie it selfe by her might be pourtraid,</l>
                  <l>Yet Others, not her selfe, for that deformitie haue paid.</l>
                  <l>Now, were our Hostesse purged of her couetous humour too,</l>
                  <l>It were a <hi>Metaphysick</hi> more than <hi>Belzebub</hi> can doe:</l>
                  <l>To whom I leaue both her and all such Hosteses, Amen:</l>
                  <l>For better matter, could we hit thereon, attends our pen.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This Toy tost-by, be now awhile contemplated vpon</l>
                  <l>The God-protected Gouernment of that sweet Queene is gon.</l>
                  <l>How happie her distaste of These, of Pope, and Papists all</l>
                  <l>Was to her selfe and Hers, and how an Edict late for <hi>Baal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Such as was <hi>Iehues,</hi> seem'd proclaim'd: for whereto els should tend</l>
                  <l>Such libertie of Trauell, or of Ours, that might defend</l>
                  <l>Euen gainst true Christians Catholikes, nick-named, but thereby</l>
                  <l>To our Religion or to <hi>Romes</hi> Affections so to trie?</l>
                  <l>Sith pregnantly is Opposite our King to Papistrie.</l>
                  <l>On These I ruminating thus into a slumber fell,</l>
                  <l>And dream'd a speaking Vision, which did humour me so well,</l>
                  <l>As would I could (which Arte cannot) it in its Essence tell.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="chapter">
               <pb n="393" facs="tcp:20257:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 100.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>E thought I did conceit the Sight that marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Stephen</hi> had,</l>
                  <l>And from that glorious Heauen descend a Maide in brightnes clad:</l>
                  <l>Her lookes had compleat Maiestie mixt with allacrious view,</l>
                  <l>Whom by that Raritie to bee <hi>Elizabeth</hi> I knew.</l>
                  <l>Friend (quoth she) small thy fame and lesse thy Fortune, howbeit</l>
                  <l>Good-will I estimate aboue birth, wealth, or fluent wit,</l>
                  <l>Thy Betters (once my Flatterers) me and themselues forgit,</l>
                  <l>Thou with thy Mite remembrest me, and I remember it.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Palinur</hi> I come not of <hi>Aeneas</hi> to intreate</l>
                  <l>Interment, it I had, and am behighted Tombrie great.</l>
                  <l>Nor come I, sorrie Soule, to thee (as short of skill iwis</l>
                  <l>As meanes to mend in Staterie aught, if were aught amis)</l>
                  <l>As quarrellous, but to applaud what as I left it is,</l>
                  <l>For which at least your prudent King and Councell boad yee blis.</l>
                  <l>Nor come I from a <hi>Limbo,</hi> for there is but Heauen and Hell,</l>
                  <l>And Soules immediatly are and continue as they fell,</l>
                  <l>Though of a <hi>Purgatorie</hi> Popes the Fable dearely sell</l>
                  <l>Of life Eternitie, of Ioyes I Infinencie haue,</l>
                  <l>Yet rests a glorifying doome beyond what heart can craue:</l>
                  <l>We are in God, and God in vs, and God and we in one</l>
                  <l>Will not, vnlesse ye will, my Realme relict be ouerthrowne.</l>
                  <l>I found it such as Papistrie affecteth it againe,</l>
                  <l>And held it contrarie spight <hi>Rome, France,</hi> and insatiat <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="394" facs="tcp:20257:31"/>
                  <l> Rebellions, and Conspiracies, and left an Heire to raigne</l>
                  <l>Me likt he should, and ioyes he doth, yet write I thus complaine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Whereas, like <hi>England,</hi> not a Realme in <hi>Europe</hi> hath and had</l>
                  <l>Such powerfull Foes and Schismes, in all so capitally bad,</l>
                  <l>And God alone hath vndertaine your Cause and made yee glad,</l>
                  <l>May seeme of your owne Policie and strength yee ouerwinne,</l>
                  <l>Of thankfulnes so little, and so much yee shew of sinne.</l>
                  <l>Wheras (Truths &amp; Times work) the Pope grew Here estrāged too,</l>
                  <l>As tirde in his attempts, and dride in all that he could doe,</l>
                  <l>Neer comen to this as, nam'd, was askt of whēce that Beast &amp; who?</l>
                  <l>How is it (though your Leagues perhaps for Statrie and for Trades</l>
                  <l>Be not amis, new times I know new Amitie perswades)</l>
                  <l>That (which I held and left restraind, &amp; whereby <hi>England</hi> thriu'd)</l>
                  <l>By tolerated Trauell, and free Souldrie is reuiu'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Romes</hi> poyson, and too patent meanes for Plots to be contriu'd?</l>
                  <l>But if be meant that so should Waspes be draind from out the Hiue,</l>
                  <l>Then penance too may Policie those that it so doth shriue:</l>
                  <l>For Altars not to arme with vs, against vs is to striue:</l>
                  <l>Religion and Subiection be each th'others Relatiue.</l>
                  <l>Now is it not as when, at once, all Kings adord the Beast,</l>
                  <l>So much more poysnous now by how much more in power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creast,</l>
                  <l>To be suspect in Citie, Towne, Court, Countrie, friendship, Feast,</l>
                  <l>Nor maruell that <hi>Rome</hi> wins so fast, and, wonne, retaines so sure,</l>
                  <l>Sith it to all is all in all, selfe-profit to procure.</l>
                  <l>The Serpent that in <hi>Eden</hi> did to Mankinds losse intice,</l>
                  <l>Is at her Councels President, to giue gainst ye aduice.</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Mahomet</hi> his Alchoran more plausable than Hers:</l>
                  <l>The cause that many a Woman, Youth, and Indigent so erres:</l>
                  <l>For easie Preies intice a Theefe, Opinion much preferres:</l>
                  <l>With Sensualitie in part permitted, and sinne bribed,</l>
                  <l>And with this Mot, <hi>Sinne be assoyld,</hi> may <hi>Rome</hi> be circumscribed.</l>
                  <l>O pestilent Religion (no Religion) that giues leaue,</l>
                  <l>Or pardon to the fowlest Sinnes, nor only doth receaue</l>
                  <pb n="395" facs="tcp:20257:31"/>
                  <l> Your Fugitiues, but them returns fraught with Instructions such</l>
                  <l>As brought, though by a beardles boy, your State may wholy tuch!</l>
                  <l>Sith <hi>Plutos</hi> Gates ope nights and daies to all will goe or come,</l>
                  <l>Shut yours to shut in yours, and theirs shut out both all and some.</l>
                  <l>Nor of your Linsie-wolsie Roofes of Peeres can I be dumme:</l>
                  <l>Nor of the <hi>Mechianisme</hi> of some your Great-Ones by the Drumme.</l>
                  <l>Me thought like <hi>Tudor</hi> her stour Sier at it last said she fround:</l>
                  <l>O God, quoth she, can Iustice sleepe where such Mis-life is found,</l>
                  <l>In President a preiudice, in law sauz godly ground?</l>
                  <l>Should such whom God &amp; Nature els haue beutifide throughtout,</l>
                  <l>For one base sinne to Vulgers be a by-word and a flout?</l>
                  <l>No, be it yet remembred that was God his feare forgot,</l>
                  <l>Who will forgiue true Penitents, and Time out-wears a blot:</l>
                  <l>If at this Charme be stopt the eares, there is a hell I wot.</l>
                  <l>There is an idle Schisme to <hi>Rome</hi> and you in Opposition,</l>
                  <l>Which, should it speede, nor she nor yee met euer like Physition:</l>
                  <l>Life for a Limme, meane Medicines without a meane applide,</l>
                  <l>Which, though contraried in Pretexts, besibs that others Pride.</l>
                  <l>Of it giue also Caution, and bid kill it in the bud:</l>
                  <l>It euer harmed where it grew, and neuer will doe good,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Britaine</hi> as a Pestilence warne that it be withstood.</l>
                  <l>Now that I mention <hi>Britaine,</hi> know that Name doth please me well:</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Brute</hi> till now a Monarchie nere of this Isle befell:</l>
                  <l>Vnion in one same Policie adde, and auoid an hell:</l>
                  <l>My Brothers Legend much against Pluralitie doth tell.</l>
                  <l>How many seuerall Lawes at once had <hi>Britaine</hi> long agoe?</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Britons</hi> theirs, the <hi>Romanes</hi> theirs, the <hi>Picts</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> also.</l>
                  <l>In neerer times (besides the <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Welsh)</hi> seauen <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings:</l>
                  <l>Vpheld so many Lawes, an Eighth with him the <hi>Dane</hi> he brings:</l>
                  <l>And all those Eight the <hi>Normaine</hi> found to Three digested, and</l>
                  <l>Of all their creames compild one Law, now <hi>Common</hi> in this Land.</l>
                  <l>Since when, attempted oft, had no Inuasion ouer-hand,</l>
                  <pb n="396" facs="tcp:20257:32"/>
                  <l> Ere when this Realme within it selfe continually did striue,</l>
                  <l>And vnto seuerall Alliants op't a way for Conquests fiue.</l>
                  <l>May Realmes, Religion, Lawes, and hearts in prosperous Vnion thriue.</l>
                  <l>But that I know be lawes in force for Sabbaths, feasts of Saints,</l>
                  <l>For Fasts, for Vagrāts, pestring now your Streets without Restraints,</l>
                  <l>I should haue thought those too prophane and warrant lawes had bin,</l>
                  <l>So common and so vncontrould is sufferance of such sin.</l>
                  <l>Taxe <hi>England,</hi> fertill in good lawes that meete with each amis,</l>
                  <l>For that it so remissiue in their Execution is.</l>
                  <l>Warne, midst such Plentie, Pleasures, &amp; this blessed Peace take heed,</l>
                  <l>Lest from Securitie therein a sudden Scourge proceed.</l>
                  <l>Who thought but all had bin as well as could the heart desire,</l>
                  <l>When all stood at the sudden doome of one false sparke of fire,</l>
                  <l>Which had effected, had not God stood <hi>Britaines</hi> Sentinell:</l>
                  <l>Most though but wōder, few praise him, bid thou pray al proue wel.</l>
                  <l>If Soules at rest for priuate wrōgs could grieue whē such appeares,</l>
                  <l>Paintings, and Pleasances of some, in stead of Mourners teares,</l>
                  <l>Accōpanying my Funeral, had grieu'd mine Eies &amp; Eares.</l>
                  <l>Did neuer Mother tender more her Childe than I the State,</l>
                  <l>Howbeit some it recompence at too vnkind a Rate:</l>
                  <l>Detractiue bookes at publique Saile, of moment so much lesse</l>
                  <l>By how much more the Authors are obseru'd how they professe.</l>
                  <l>In Heauen was wondred that on Earth an Edict should be seene,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>English</hi> should not scandalize their late deceased Queene,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lycurgus,</hi> as of <hi>Patricid,</hi> that Law had left out cleene,</l>
                  <l>Of such Ingratitude so small Expectance: though not rare</l>
                  <l>The lust of Nouelties, sometimes from Quailes to Garlick-fare.</l>
                  <l>But ye that thought I liu'd too long had found I dide too soone,</l>
                  <l>Had not God better preordaind Succession than your Boone,</l>
                  <l>Which like to that of <hi>Aesops</hi> Frogs had varied, till at last</l>
                  <l>Some Storke had plaid ye <hi>Rex,</hi> and then had worser pleasd than past.</l>
                  <pb n="397" facs="tcp:20257:32"/>
                  <l> By <hi>Scipio</hi> and by <hi>Caesar</hi> so dealt <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Carthage</hi> so</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Hānibal,</hi> and <hi>Greece</hi> her Friends found <hi>Greece</hi> their greatest Foe:</l>
                  <l>The tyrannie of pleball tongues most good most vndergoe.</l>
                  <l>In few not knowing why malign'd, nor why Malignors haue</l>
                  <l>Of late retracted, <hi>Romes</hi> except, that hate me in my Graue,</l>
                  <l>Let it suffice I pardon all, and blessed may proceede</l>
                  <l>The Gouernment, of <hi>Romerie</hi> and new <hi>Anabaptisme</hi> freede:</l>
                  <l>And so farewell. And so I wakt, that wisht prolonged sleepe,</l>
                  <l>For when I found I did but dreame I could not then but weepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Farre be it though should any thinke the Vision could be Her,</l>
                  <l>To doubt whose Soule to be with God were out of doubt to erre▪</l>
                  <l>But most-what seemed said we might for veritie auer.</l>
                  <l>The neuer idle minde, in like Respondencie of zeale,</l>
                  <l>Not seldome by <hi>Phantasma</hi> thus in Sleepes doth Soothes reueale.</l>
                  <l>But idely hath and ouerlong been dreamed, think may some:</l>
                  <l>Much more Elation though would this Relation well become,</l>
                  <l>Euen she was dream't-off &amp; the dreame, That for her worth, &amp; This</l>
                  <l>In it Particulars inuite discourse much lesse omis.</l>
                  <l>Yet so hath been digressed and so dreamed as almost</l>
                  <l>Our Muse, that scarce is entred <hi>Wales,</hi> it selfe in <hi>Wales</hi> hath lost.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="book">
            <pb n="398" facs="tcp:20257:33"/>
            <head>THE SIXTEENTH BOOKE <hi>OF ALBIONS ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="101" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 101.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Outh<hi>-Wales</hi> was yet intierly <hi>Welsh,</hi> and <hi>Rees ap-Tudor</hi> Prince,</l>
                  <l>When Rebels wrought that <hi>England</hi> it hath owned euer since:</l>
                  <l>And thence the <hi>English</hi> by Degrees all <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bria</hi> did inuaide:</l>
                  <l>May neuer ciuill discord in this Isle re-reare be praide,</l>
                  <l>Or if (the euer-losse of All) be sought no forren aide.</l>
                  <l>For West<hi>-Wales</hi> (also <hi>Rees</hi> his Right) Rebellion first begunne,</l>
                  <l>Inuiting <hi>Englist-Normaine</hi> Aides, that it and South<hi>-Wales</hi> wonne,</l>
                  <l>And in a long and asperous Warre all <hi>Wales</hi> ere they had done.</l>
                  <l>Impacably possessed though, till rather selfe-accord,</l>
                  <l>Than often Armies wrought that we in milder Lawes it lord.</l>
                  <l>This noble and vndanted Prince had had an ouer-hand</l>
                  <l>Of diuers Rebels, <hi>Iestin</hi> and one <hi>Eneon,</hi> in the Land</l>
                  <l>Of chiefe command, compact that whē this <hi>Eneon</hi> should be sped</l>
                  <l>Of Aids from <hi>England,</hi> he in liew should <hi>Iestins</hi> Daughter wed:</l>
                  <l>In birth and Education one right nobly and well bred.</l>
                  <l>Great in King <hi>William Rufus</hi> Court <hi>Fitzhamon</hi> was, and hee</l>
                  <l>To expedite against Prince <hi>Rees</hi> an Armie did decree.</l>
                  <pb n="399" facs="tcp:20257:33"/>
                  <l> Now <hi>Eneon, Iestins</hi> Agent, thus of <hi>English</hi> Troupes prouided,</l>
                  <l>And other Rebels adding Powers, by swords was thus decided:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rees</hi> (euer earst victorious) now in valiant fight was kild,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fitz-hamon</hi> and his Knights had all behited them fulfild,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Eneon</hi> only was gainsaid the Marrage promisd him:</l>
                  <l>Who therefore to the <hi>English</hi> Ships, that sailes and tacklings trim</l>
                  <l>To haue departed, posted, and recalling them, perswaded</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fitzhamon</hi> so gainst <hi>Iestin</hi> that <hi>Glamorgan</hi> he inuaded:</l>
                  <l>And, though no easie Conquest, yet he conquerd it at last,</l>
                  <l>Which thence frō him and his braue Knights frō heire to heire hath past.</l>
                  <l>These were the first of Alliants that in <hi>Wales</hi> Possession wonne,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Rees</hi> thus slaine the Principate of South<hi>-Wales</hi> so was done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now <hi>Iestin</hi> dead, no maruell that his daughter could not brooke</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Eneon</hi> cause thereof, for she thus orphanag'd forsooke</l>
                  <l>Her conquered Countrie, and vnknowne to all, vnlesse to One</l>
                  <l>Her slaughtred Fathers friend in his late fortune ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>Whom now she faind her Father (nor her father lou'd her more)</l>
                  <l>Escaping, wealthily a Farme in <hi>England</hi> they did store:</l>
                  <l>Whereas they liu'd a countrie life, belou'd, in State not poore:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Margaret</hi> (so now her name) where euer heard or seene,</l>
                  <l>For beauty and sweet hauour was pronounst the Country-Queene:</l>
                  <l>And by how much more bashful, &amp; of tongue-pride mildly spare,</l>
                  <l>Seem'd carelesse clenly in attire, her huswifrie did care,</l>
                  <l>Nor scorning nor affecting Loue, so much more seem'd she rare,</l>
                  <l>And rather than in haughtines did fault in too-submis,</l>
                  <l>A fault the contrarie whereof in bastard Gentrie is.</l>
                  <l>How often would the Swaines prepare their Morrice &amp; their May</l>
                  <l>To haue a sight of her, when all enamoured went their way?</l>
                  <l>The sprewsest Citie-Lads for her would faine the Countrie-aire,</l>
                  <l>And that their prouder Girles had but adultrate beauties swaire,</l>
                  <l>Oft Courtiers faind or, Milke for thirst, or for their Hawke a Pigion,</l>
                  <l>When, might they parle with her, no more was mingd of such pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigiō.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Combinement thus of Nature and of Vertue is admirde:</l>
                  <pb n="400" facs="tcp:20257:34"/>
                  <l> Though Natures gifts are oft with Arte by most too much attirde:</l>
                  <l>But chiefly cleered Scalpes of haire with Periwigs supplide,</l>
                  <l>To God and Nature sinne me thinkes, and men at least deride</l>
                  <l>Gray-headed Crownes and vulgar Stuffe that so are finifide.</l>
                  <l>For who can lesse than smile that sees vnstanch and riueld faces,</l>
                  <l>To shelter coylie vnderneath Fannes, Tifnies, Maskes, Bongraces?</l>
                  <l>O Cousnag to an amorous Eye, nor thence but thus ensues</l>
                  <l>That such, not such as they would seeme, by such intice our viewes</l>
                  <l>To censure them for also vaine, whose foule were els no newes.</l>
                  <l>Nay, why should faces faire indeed bo-peepe behinde a Fanne,</l>
                  <l>Or be conceild in Satten, now Vermiliond, now drugd wanne,</l>
                  <l>Or any hold it Ornament to owne an arted haire,</l>
                  <l>Sith men esteeme the fairest foule that so is fowly faire?</l>
                  <l>Giue me a Girle that is her-selfe, Compounds if ye compare</l>
                  <l>With Simples, be not Physicks, but sophisticated ware:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Minerua</hi> suffereth violence when <hi>Phao</hi> makes her faire:</l>
                  <l>May such be disarithmetickt his Creatures that are.</l>
                  <l>Dust, Wormes-meate, Rottennes, that thinke your borrowed beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties rare,</l>
                  <l>That so obseru'd and sottishly from your Creation square,</l>
                  <l>And not at all your pride-sick Soules but falsed faces care,</l>
                  <l>Yea, and essentiall Beauties that of vertuous mindes be bare,</l>
                  <l>Amend your such Amisses which should hoped Eyes despaire.</l>
                  <l>And ye that haue the Aire parfum'd, bathe oft in Lotions sweete,</l>
                  <l>Be borne like <hi>Romes</hi> Triumphants, Earth vnworthie your coy feete,</l>
                  <l>Glitter in gold, pearles, pretious stones, haue beautie in it pride,</l>
                  <l>With all that Ornament, wealth, Arte can any way prouide,</l>
                  <l>Or soone must die, or see an age shall shew in you such change,</l>
                  <l>As, looking back to youth, your selues shal to your selues seem strāge.</l>
                  <l>Gray haires aboue your furrowed Brows, Noses &amp; Mouthes cōtract,</l>
                  <l>Lanke in-bowd Cheeks, like Lips &amp; Chins, teeth rottē, &amp; teeth lackt,</l>
                  <l>Brawn-falne, crāp, stitches, belching, &amp; much els as much vnsweet,</l>
                  <l>With aches, palsies, and moe such your hastning Ends shall greet,</l>
                  <l>And, dead, a million such not worth the simplest winding sheete.</l>
                  <pb n="401" facs="tcp:20257:34"/>
                  <l> If so, as so, then sooth good sooth in this said one, say I,</l>
                  <l>Not borne at all were happier, borne, were happie soone to die,</l>
                  <l>So progresse we in Vanities, pursues vs Miserie.</l>
                  <l>Sith in these transitorie Turnes our Bodies thus transmute,</l>
                  <l>To pampering, painting, prowding them meere vanitie impute.</l>
                  <l>But chiefely Nature wrongd by Arte, of Prowdnes more than need,</l>
                  <l>Cannot but to the Actors shame, mislike in others breede.</l>
                  <l>For why? firme liking of a thing imagined, thinks me,</l>
                  <l>Should quash in them imagin or imagined would be.</l>
                  <l>Who knowes false fire and feares? Who fat with painted meates they see?</l>
                  <l>Who flies a paper Giant? feares an Asse in Lyons skinne?</l>
                  <l>Who fees a noted Idiot that with Arte a Cause must winne?</l>
                  <l>A Coward armd like <hi>Hercules</hi> who is it doth not scorne?</l>
                  <l>Esteemes a Kyte a Faulcon, though so belled and so borne?</l>
                  <l>Then actiuely and passiuely much more, me thinketh, might</l>
                  <l>Those needlesse Curiosities with Nature that condight</l>
                  <l>Be apprehended meere Offence of Notion and to Sight.</l>
                  <l>For can we thinke prompt Is not is? If not, what seeke we more</l>
                  <l>Than as lists God naturalize, subtract, adde, strike, restore?</l>
                  <l>Deuotion heathenish did and doth vile Creatures adore,</l>
                  <l>Should Christians in a Christian thē count Blemish Eie sights Sore?</l>
                  <l>No, Mightie▪Ones are to themselues for Placcards, rich, and poore,</l>
                  <l>If virtuous, though deformed, hold full waight in wisemens Lore.</l>
                  <l>Nor meant is here but modestly may arted be attier</l>
                  <l>To Natures scarres, and cleanlied all doth decencie requier.</l>
                  <l>Nor beate we here malignantly at sacred Beauties Luster,</l>
                  <l>But to contemplate it aright proud Featur-fers we muster.</l>
                  <l>And be it that Prescription doth naturalize in Court</l>
                  <l>Some Errors to an habit, held for Ornament and Port,</l>
                  <l>(For things in some vnseemly are not such to some of Sort)</l>
                  <l>Yet might, me thinks, be wisht the Court were also prowder than</l>
                  <l>That Vulgers should in Tinctures, Tiers, Maske, Fardingale, and Fan</l>
                  <l>Coriue, a Gill be Lady-like, and Iack a Gentelman.</l>
                  <pb n="402" facs="tcp:20257:35"/>
                  <l> To Blowses, aping Niceties and <hi>Ante-physicks</hi> arting,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Aesops</hi> Iay displumed me like guerdon of peruerting.</l>
                  <l>Now roome Sirs for a Toy a Troth, els haue I heard a Lie:</l>
                  <l>But howsoeuer, be it told for no Diuinitie.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 102.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>As once a Drudge, a sturdie Royle, whom Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture friended so,</l>
                  <l>As not the proudest head than hers a fairer haire did owe:</l>
                  <l>So well her Lady likt thereof as, soundly whilst she sleepes,</l>
                  <l>She sheares it off, for losse of which in vaine poore <hi>Malken</hi> weepes.</l>
                  <l>Where was it, or who did the deede she could not learne of long,</l>
                  <l>Till chanst her finde another haire old Lumber cast among.</l>
                  <l>Her office was to emptie all that had of empting neede,</l>
                  <l>With Ingresse free and Regresse for performance of that deede.</l>
                  <l>I wot not how it came to passe, the Ladies Head-geere (she</l>
                  <l>A sleepe) was off, so <hi>Malken</hi> chanst her haireles front to see.</l>
                  <l>Soone fetcht she, and confers the haire earst found with hers y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> slept,</l>
                  <l>Her owne too with a Perwig that lay there, most choisely kept,</l>
                  <l>And in that Scrutanie resolues, nor so resoluing errs,</l>
                  <l>It found to haue bin Madams, it was perwigged once Hers.</l>
                  <l>This tooke she thence, That left she there. Anon came Gallants gay</l>
                  <l>To frollike with her Ladiship, and her vp-rising stay.</l>
                  <l>Where cushend was the Perwig there was found a dustie Maine,</l>
                  <l>The Ladie chafes, her Chamberers seeke euery nooke in vaine.</l>
                  <l>Meane while, all tatterd, durtie, &amp; whose chaers her face did smudge,</l>
                  <pb n="403" facs="tcp:20257:35"/>
                  <l> In comes, from seruing hogs or like, the rude perwigged Drudge,</l>
                  <l>Salutes the Guests, offers to kisse, be kist, good sport they haue</l>
                  <l>To see such foule from top to toe her only head so braue.</l>
                  <l>Well well (quoth <hi>Malken)</hi> scoffe and scorne, My Lady is abed</l>
                  <l>A Bodie only, Manners would some greet yee in her stead,</l>
                  <l>And who should rather than my selfe that long haue been her head?</l>
                  <l>Mine had she not shorne off and worne (eie-liquor here she shead)</l>
                  <l>I had (beshrew her Maddamship) ere now (ha ho) been wead.</l>
                  <l>Thus sham'd shee her might shame, for then were Perwigs newly bread,</l>
                  <l>Though since too many, modest els, are in that Art misled:</l>
                  <l>Vaine Eies not vnderstanding Thoughts howbeit so are fed.</l>
                  <l>But yee, and yee whom Nature hath or Fortune prowded know,</l>
                  <l>That vade ye shall as flowers forgot when and where yee did grow.</l>
                  <l>For none, for whatsoeuer, hath or can themselues suruiue,</l>
                  <l>But them vnto Posterities our Pennes preserue aliue,</l>
                  <l>And famous or infamous shall at least those great-Ones be,</l>
                  <l>That shall or shall not in this Life that future life fore-see:</l>
                  <l>Howbeit, Perpetuitie Impenitents feare yee</l>
                  <l>Of sinnes Rewarde, much more than all that All can else decree.</l>
                  <l>Deathes Certenty, whē, where, &amp; how vncertain, life throughout,</l>
                  <l>Should curbe all selfe-Indulgencie and flesh so proudlie stout,</l>
                  <l>That but as in a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> elaboureth about.</l>
                  <l>Our Losses, Crosses, Passions, and Affections passing-by,</l>
                  <l>Passe but along the Currant from our Births vntill we die,</l>
                  <l>And finde we shall our <hi>Infancie</hi> a dreame of, who knowes what?</l>
                  <l>The booke and birch to <hi>Childhood</hi> Checke more feelinglie than that:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Adolescencie</hi> may be said A meere or merrie Madnes:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Manhood</hi> sildome sheweth more it bouldnes than in badnes:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Old-age</hi> (in carke, drifts, shifts y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sweats) or ends when enters thriuing,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Age-re-childed,</hi> decrepate (lifes vtmost) stints all striuing:</l>
                  <l>Then Carrions be our Carcases, and to our Soules remaines</l>
                  <l>For well or ill here done the doome of endles Ioyes or Paines.</l>
                  <l>Then blessed infinitly thou beyond worlds pompe or pelfe,</l>
                  <pb n="404" facs="tcp:20257:36"/>
                  <l> That louedst God aboue all things, thy Neighbour as thy selfe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But now to <hi>Iestins</hi> Daughter where we left proceed we heere:</l>
                  <l>To her reputed Father was a Yeoman dwelling neere,</l>
                  <l>Richer, as is the Adage, by full many a Sheepe and Oxe,</l>
                  <l>By farnesse from a Gentleman, a Lawyer, and a Foxe.</l>
                  <l>Nor squard, as chanst, the Parson for tithe whit-meats, lambe, wool, Shocks,</l>
                  <l>As some not pardoning poorest Soules their pēce for hēs &amp; cocks,</l>
                  <l>When that h'as all he all consumes on peacock Pride and smocks.</l>
                  <l>This Yeoman was a Iustice to himselfe, his Neighbours all</l>
                  <l>Him loued, and he loued them. If Variance hapt to fall,</l>
                  <l>They went not to such Worships as like Tyrants men miscall:</l>
                  <l>Which for couragious Iusticeship must be to them ascribed,</l>
                  <l>Though at an Outlawrie their wits, some partiall, and some bribed,</l>
                  <l>Must euermore be fawned on, haue Presents, purchase cheape,</l>
                  <l>Carts <hi>gratis</hi> sent to their Remoues, and men their Corne to reape,</l>
                  <l>Presses or Impositions els on him defects they heape,</l>
                  <l>When their Retainors royst and wrong, yet out of Iustice leape.</l>
                  <l>But if shall one, els honest, erre through choler, vrg'd abuse,</l>
                  <l>Or casually, their grudge or gaer admit no termes of truse:</l>
                  <l>When desprate Ruffins fraught with faults finde readily a Meuse,</l>
                  <l>Or not at all are question'd, as sin-quitted by sins-vse.</l>
                  <l>Yea, are not of Commissoned themselues some that sometimes</l>
                  <l>Doe borrow of their Iusticeship for <hi>Caesar-</hi>dues and Crimes?</l>
                  <l>But petite Trespasses and Those were yeelded faults and mended</l>
                  <l>Were silenced, and none so great but Neighbours friendly ended</l>
                  <l>Where dwelt this Yeoman, rich in State, yet richer in a Sonne</l>
                  <l>Frugall and honest, richest when to Daughter-in-law he wonne</l>
                  <l>This faire <hi>Glamorganean,</hi> that did termes of Gentrie shunne.</l>
                  <l>But long conceald affection how it fadged superseade,</l>
                  <l>Vntill the Yongmans letter that to her he wrote yee reade.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="chapter">
               <pb n="405" facs="tcp:20257:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 103.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat thou beest, <hi>Pegge,</hi> in better heale than I my selfe am now</l>
                  <l>I wish, or that like sick for me as I for thee wert thou.</l>
                  <l>The cause that now I write it is to let thee wit That I,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Cupid</hi> long since branded thine, must thee mate-quaint, or die.</l>
                  <l>Small rest, God wot, a nights, few meales a day take I, loue-sick,</l>
                  <l>And little heart in Possets, sops, a supping, or a Chick:</l>
                  <l>Then loue me, <hi>Pegge,</hi> fornenter when is blabd abroad my plight,</l>
                  <l>On thy too squamish Maidenhead the crime thereof doe light.</l>
                  <l>But, wot'st thy what? I with our Cart haue bin whileare at Court,</l>
                  <l>And saw the King (God saue his grace) &amp; mought he heare report,</l>
                  <l>How vs his Officers doe buse, almost in euery sort.</l>
                  <l>Thy father would haue feoft on thee a Courtnall, faith t'was well</l>
                  <l>Thou scap'st him, for if he be good, then none be bad in Hell.</l>
                  <l>Lord, how he swaggerd in his silks, and seeing me by chance,</l>
                  <l>As Peacocks viewed spread their tailes did he himselfe aduance!</l>
                  <l>Yet once my fathers house was all his helpe: but let him passe</l>
                  <l>With that same lustie horse that scornd the Millers loden Asse,</l>
                  <l>Till turnd out lame, this one had corne, that other scarcely grasse:</l>
                  <l>Such bastard Courtnals serue but Turns, besibbing Coyns of brasse.</l>
                  <l>Thou, for t'hart monstrous faire, thinkst me not fine enough, I, but</l>
                  <l>Perhaps wert better fancie me than such a Lustie-gut.</l>
                  <l>Though with gay Brokerie may seeme he casteth thee to win,</l>
                  <l>I better borrow could of Pride than he the silken Sin:</l>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="chapter">
               <pb n="408" facs="tcp:20257:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 104.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His with a peece of Rie-paist seald, sent, and receiued, she</l>
                  <l>Did meditate thereon, although obtuse in phrase yee see.</l>
                  <l>The Surface of him-selfe, thinks she, exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd is herein,</l>
                  <l>May seeme he cannot flatter, nor me Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie shall win,</l>
                  <l>Oft Praysers are to vs as is to Birds the Fowlers gin.</l>
                  <l>Alas, what keepe of Beautie, which indeede is but a blast?</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Non-proficient</hi> at the least it must be at the last:</l>
                  <l>Though thereof <hi>Poeans</hi> in mens Mouthes as in a Mould are cast.</l>
                  <l>Fooles are we, and as foolishly doe Men aduance our pride,</l>
                  <l>That vnto prizing Praysers tongues our tickled eares hath tide,</l>
                  <l>Els our facundious Fooles might we more than they vs deride:</l>
                  <l>To see them gallop <hi>Thersites</hi> when listeth them to crake,</l>
                  <l>To out sigh <hi>Schyno</hi> when they feare a foyle and <hi>Troy</hi> would take:</l>
                  <l>But shadowes we for substances <hi>Narcissus</hi> like mistake.</l>
                  <l>For edged by such Artists, and they once possest of vs,</l>
                  <l>The fairest Faire is foule or foole, and <hi>Pigs-nie</hi> but a <hi>Pusse,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>A-per-se,</hi> obserued earst as Weathercocks doe winde,</l>
                  <l>Oft to a too imperious Lord is, as nere She, declinde,</l>
                  <l>Or glorious trash and Titles, whence ambitious thoughts proceed,</l>
                  <l>Make Others enuie vs, or vs betraieth to vn-heed.</l>
                  <l>O neuer lost Humilitie, nor Haughtinesse did win,</l>
                  <l>An honest Man and meanes to liue is and my boone hath bin.</l>
                  <l>The Greatest in her Greatnes oft I see hath discontents:</l>
                  <pb n="409" facs="tcp:20257:37"/>
                  <l> Nor doth an happie life consist in Titles, Robes or Rents.</l>
                  <l>The Court hath been, the Countrie is to me familiar, either</l>
                  <l>Not quit of Tediousnes, yet This than That preferre I rather.</l>
                  <l>Among our Cattell, in our Fields, at Home may losse and harmes</l>
                  <l>Vn-patient vs, farre diffrent though impatient Courts and Farmes.</l>
                  <l>There Quarrel drifteth euē to blood, to Wealths losse, or disgrace,</l>
                  <l>Here simply, at the least to saue Expence, they Peace imbrace:</l>
                  <l>Or if too busie some-where Some, they are esteemed bace.</l>
                  <l>The bodies glorious Ornaments, and gawdie Tires for head,</l>
                  <l>(Extracts from Worme-webs, Mettles, Birds, yea thefts from her is dead)</l>
                  <l>Shew more of sin, serue lesser thā a fleece of wool in stead.</l>
                  <l>Were Pride no such Practitioner and Denizen allowd,</l>
                  <l>I should haue been an Infidell that Pride could be so prowd.</l>
                  <l>But Earth, Aire, Graue, Arte, Hell, &amp; al gainst Nature now combine,</l>
                  <l>Whereby our Soules shew duskie whilst our gilded Carrions shine.</l>
                  <l>Refraine but Court and Citie then of neither finde we mis,</l>
                  <l>A Dairie-dame, that minds not more, than Madam merrier is:</l>
                  <l>Food, cloath, and habour competent should as thinke I suffise,</l>
                  <l>Vpon the matter who hath more whom Fortune most supplies?</l>
                  <l>And who be they that are not Earth, and must returne thereto?</l>
                  <l>Then only Vertue vnto vs best Offices can doe.</l>
                  <l>Now to an Husband: <hi>Gilberd</hi> is no Gallant yet no Gull,</l>
                  <l>Not learned but well limmed, and couragious to the full,</l>
                  <l>Frugall yet frollike, speakes with sense, his Breeding if respected,</l>
                  <l>In wealth sufficient, neuer of Dishonestie detected,</l>
                  <l>What would I more? Such should not, nor of me shal be reiected,</l>
                  <l>Mine is a Loue preordinate to be to him subiected:</l>
                  <l>Nor Fortune aught disparageth that loue to loue directeth:</l>
                  <l>A Woman to a Man is all that loue twixt all effecteth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>At modest Opportunities she yeelds her Loues consent:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Gilberd</hi> wiued <hi>Margaret,</hi> to Eithers hearts content.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="chapter">
               <pb n="410" facs="tcp:20257:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 105.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Itz-hamon</hi> and his Complices thus hauing broke the Ice,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>England</hi> Emulation did <hi>Newmarch</hi> for <hi>Wales</hi> intice,</l>
                  <l>With Armes (as brauely answered of <hi>Welsh)</hi> did he inuade</l>
                  <l>The Cautreds three of <hi>Brechnock,</hi> and thereof a Conquest made:</l>
                  <l>And married <hi>Nest, Nests</hi> Daughter, that King <hi>Gruffyths</hi> Daughter was,</l>
                  <l>And had a Sonne, <hi>Mahel,</hi> to whom his great Possessions passe,</l>
                  <l>A worthy Knight: But <hi>Nest,</hi> whē was her Husband <hi>Newmarch</hi> dead,</l>
                  <l>A too licentious life with one of her beloued lead.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mahel</hi> her Sonne, ill brooking it, fought with and wounded sore</l>
                  <l>The same his Mothers Paramour, She much inrag'd therefore.</l>
                  <l>And dares the Primecocks interrupt me in my loue, quoth she?</l>
                  <l>Or thinks he vnreuenged it shall ouerpassed be?</l>
                  <l>Forgets he Loue and Ladies to be Relatiues, and those</l>
                  <l>But bastard Gentries that themselues not amorously repose?</l>
                  <l>What Gallant almost holds it not the pietie of Clownes</l>
                  <l>To haue but strict-confined loue in <hi>Hymaenean</hi> bownes?</l>
                  <l>For Husband, Wife be tired Tearmes, Friend, Seruant courtly sounds.</l>
                  <l>Who hath not heard amongst the Gods that <hi>Mars</hi> did <hi>Venus</hi> court?</l>
                  <l>Then sentenced, not yet repeald, a tolerable sport:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Penelope</hi> is Poëtrie, <hi>Lucretia</hi> fain'd report.</l>
                  <l>Doe set her to the Distaffe, Batch, the Milk-paile, and such Chares,</l>
                  <l>Hath all Attendance, Pleasures, Ease, lies soft, and finely fares,</l>
                  <l>If these haue no Prerogatiue, nor be Preparatiues</l>
                  <pb n="411" facs="tcp:20257:38"/>
                  <l> To more than cōmon Courage, for no Saints such Maids or Wiues:</l>
                  <l>Yet great and wisemen winke thereat, and liue the quieter liues,</l>
                  <l>For nere the sooner her soule his possesseth he that striues.</l>
                  <l>Grant must I that our Chaplaines well doe Chastitie commend,</l>
                  <l>Yet Venall intimate they Lust sith so themselues offend.</l>
                  <l>At least such as my selfe, not old, and in my Widowhood,</l>
                  <l>May plead the same in Pardon, or my fault as thus make good:</l>
                  <l>My Birth and State be greater than I yet a Husband finde,</l>
                  <l>Meane while I am no Votarie, nor mortifide in minde:</l>
                  <l>Some, and of Sort, haue been that haue (their wickednes the more)</l>
                  <l>Euen whilst they liu'd in wedlock plaid hand-ouer-head the whore.</l>
                  <l>Such neuer I: yet must belie my selfe for such, els how</l>
                  <l>Should I reuenge me of the Boy that hath abusde me now?</l>
                  <l>Adde that I wantond wedded, as now widowed, singly this,</l>
                  <l>And ioyntly this and that will be but nine daies Chatiwis:</l>
                  <l>And what of little prattle more that to my purpose is?</l>
                  <l>Audacious Boy, that durst diuulge the amours of thy Mother,</l>
                  <l>That impudencie, know thou, shall from me beget another,</l>
                  <l>And to a Sister shall transferre a Births-right from a Brother.</l>
                  <l>Long I, and ouerlong, haue liu'd if that my Cradle now</l>
                  <l>Shall be my Tutor, let them that haue Patience it allow:</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Meleagers</hi> Mother I my selfe to <hi>Mahel</hi> vow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She, winged thus by <hi>Nemesis,</hi> soone speeding to the King,</l>
                  <l>Reueales her owne dishonour, so his liuelihood to wring</l>
                  <l>From her own Sonne, and weepingly this Cuckoe-Song did sing.</l>
                  <l>The Victor of <hi>Brechina</hi> to your Scepter <hi>Newmarch</hi> dead,</l>
                  <l>My noble Husband (ah, would I had died in his stead,</l>
                  <l>She said, as seeming soothly said, her teares did second so)</l>
                  <l>Did I abuse, and for the Crime this Pennance vnder-goe,</l>
                  <l>Besides my Conscience-scruple, that my selfe my selfe defame</l>
                  <l>Before your Highnes, for it now too much imports the same.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mahel</hi> my Sonne (ah, would he were not scandalously such,</l>
                  <l>But for he is, it is it that so deeply doth me touch)</l>
                  <pb n="412" facs="tcp:20257:39"/>
                  <l> I bore in Bastardie, and for I therein did amis,</l>
                  <l>I hold me iustly plagued that my Plague a Bastard is.</l>
                  <l>I haue a vertuous Daughter by my valerous Husband, She</l>
                  <l>Inherit should his State: Vouchsafe, my Leage, it so may be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Was ministred an oth to her, that swore her sayings true:</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Mahel</hi> to his Sister so she great Possessions drew.</l>
                  <l>This noble lustie Gentleman land-stripped thus and then,</l>
                  <l>Grew thenceforth shie of Women, and a <hi>Timon</hi> vnto Men.</l>
                  <l>The Mother dide in Obloquie, the Daughter wedded was</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Milo</hi> Earle of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and from their loynes did pas</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Bruses, Bohunes, Staffords,</hi> all great Nobles in this Land:</l>
                  <l>Yet in this Propagation great great Crosses vnderstand:</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Bruses</hi> only now be spoke, sith <hi>Wales</hi> is now in hand.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 106.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Illiam de-Bruse,</hi> of <hi>Brechnock</hi> Lord, inuited to a feast</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sitsilt,</hi> of honourable Birth, and Others not the least</l>
                  <l>Of South<hi>-Wales</hi> Gentrie, newly then from armour reconcilde</l>
                  <l>To this <hi>de-Bruse,</hi> who brooded hate &amp; hatcht it whilst he smilde.</l>
                  <l>For whether (which he after fain'd) for slaughtred brother late</l>
                  <l>Reuenge, or diffrent Sentences in things they then debate,</l>
                  <l>Were motiues to the Murthers that he acted, was too true</l>
                  <l>Wrong'd Rites of Hospitalitie on him Heauens vengeance drew.</l>
                  <l>A signall giuen, his Seruants, arm'd and ambusht to that end,</l>
                  <l>Slew those his Guests: so dangerous is a Foe reuerst a friend.</l>
                  <pb n="413" facs="tcp:20257:39"/>
                  <l> Not so content, he posteth to the murthred <hi>Sitsilts</hi> Place,</l>
                  <l>And slew his Infant-Sonne before the suppliant Mothers face.</l>
                  <l>Who, when she saw her louely Babe, whom lately she did hugge,</l>
                  <l>Whilst that he smiled on her lips or sported with her dugge,</l>
                  <l>Sprawle in his guiltles gore, and he that stabbed stabbing still,</l>
                  <l>She nakt her breast, and said: so much (though not so much so ill)</l>
                  <l>May here be done, ah, be it done, least leasure serue I pray</l>
                  <l>That vnto thee and thine, grant God, befall as fowle a Day.</l>
                  <l>Too too obdurate Sauage, if euen thou thy selfe shouldst see</l>
                  <l>A Babe of thine bleed as bleeds mine, how might it torture thee?</l>
                  <l>But bard were thine their Mothers Breasts: from home they strāgers so,</l>
                  <l>The lesser thou canst apprehend a Parents ioy or wo.</l>
                  <l>My Nurserie of this in me a doubled Nature bread,</l>
                  <l>His smiles my Cordales, griefe my gall, death rēders me but dead.</l>
                  <l>Had he (ah, had he) liu'd I had reciprocally spead.</l>
                  <l>Wretch, stay, Good stay that stab (he meant a stab) perhaps my teares</l>
                  <l>May balme those past, for yet me thinks a little life appeares.</l>
                  <l>O be my God for that poore Good! Sweet hart-root, Mam is here:</l>
                  <l>Is here? now woe is me that thou of helpe art nere the neere.</l>
                  <l>No, he is gon, alas h'is gon, yet I liue, liue I? no,</l>
                  <l>But as a Ghost, at least sweet Babe with thee would I were so,</l>
                  <l>To be this Tyrants terror till he hence to hell shall goe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then casteth she her self vpon her Sonne that breath'd his last:</l>
                  <l>Nor goler blead his wounds but that her eies shead teares as fast.</l>
                  <l>Her face admirde for faire, besmeard with blood-mixt teares, did adde</l>
                  <l>The veiw more tragick: And as she this saying often had,</l>
                  <l>Reuenge it, <hi>Sitsilt,</hi> happie yet in absence from this sight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bruse</hi> said in scoffe she spake too late, his life had bod good night:</l>
                  <l>And laughing left the Lady such as <hi>Niobe</hi> for like:</l>
                  <l>Yet spead her Prayers, him and his God diuersly did strike.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bruse</hi> dide in Exile, his proud wife in Prison, one their Sonne</l>
                  <l>Was st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ru'd, another braind as he his head-strong horse did run:</l>
                  <l>And of that Progenie throughout, long nobled in De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</l>
                  <pb n="414" facs="tcp:20257:40"/>
                  <l> Our Histories tragediously doe varie hard Euents.</l>
                  <l>To our Iniustice Iustice thus is God: repent, amend,</l>
                  <l>Blood-drifters and Oppressors, els Hell, worse than thus, your End.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 107.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough to the Kings of <hi>England</hi> their Deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion got was much</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Powys,</hi> West, and South<hi>-Wales,</hi> by the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> and the <hi>Duch:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet was our second <hi>Henry</hi> by a second <hi>Rees</hi> so plide</l>
                  <l>(By North<hi>-Wales</hi> Princes also, thrice that Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell bid and bide)</l>
                  <l>With Armes and Stratagems, as like did neuer him betide,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Stephen,</hi> or his rebell Sonnes, <hi>French, Irish, Scots</hi> or any,</l>
                  <l>Himselfe escaping hardly with the losse of Souldiers many.</l>
                  <l>* <hi>Crogen,</hi> a Terme vsde in reproch of <hi>Welsh-men,</hi> rather might</l>
                  <l>Reproch the <hi>English,</hi> that with them did there defected fight.</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Henries</hi> Armie none approcht that Passage but were kild,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Welsh-Crogen,</hi> in memoriall of that Slaughter, therefore hild</l>
                  <l>A Terme reuengefull, when came <hi>Welsh</hi> to hand: as who would say,</l>
                  <l>* Like Mercie as at <hi>Crogen</hi> ours receiued we repay.</l>
                  <l>And though write some the <hi>Welsh</hi> preuail'd more by their Scite thā swords,</l>
                  <l>Yet Enuies-selfe must grant that <hi>Wales</hi> had, and braue men affords:</l>
                  <l>Yea, had not been suborned <hi>Wales</hi> against it selfe had faild</l>
                  <l>That <hi>England,</hi> labouring it so long and dearely, had preuaild.</l>
                  <l>Great was Prince <hi>Owen Gwyneth,</hi> but Prince <hi>Lewlin</hi> Monarke more,</l>
                  <l>Except King <hi>Arthur,</hi> none in <hi>Wales</hi> had greater been before.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Rufus</hi> till first <hi>Edwards</hi> Raigne North<hi>-Wales</hi> held <hi>England</hi> tack,</l>
                  <pb n="415" facs="tcp:20257:40"/>
                  <l> But then did rather loyall hearts than wonted Prowesse lacke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lewlin</hi> next to great <hi>Lewlins</hi> sonne Prince <hi>Dauid (Gladis</hi> wiude</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Mortimer</hi> put-by) then rulde, and much by Armes achiude.</l>
                  <l>But who against that Ages <hi>Mars</hi> first <hi>Edward</hi> might hold-out?</l>
                  <l>Yet twice this <hi>Lewlin</hi> held him wag, and thirdly had no doubt,</l>
                  <l>Had not he bin betraid and slaine at <hi>Buelht,</hi> a Warrior stout.</l>
                  <l>Last Prince of very <hi>Britons,</hi> that from <hi>Brute</hi> vntill that day</l>
                  <l>Had, in some part within this Isle, continued regall sway</l>
                  <l>Two thousand and fiue hundred yeeres, two yeres if taine away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Edward,</hi> presuming <hi>Wales</hi> now won, the <hi>Welsh</hi> with commō voice</l>
                  <l>Of any Prince, vnles <hi>Welsh</hi> borne, protested gainst the choice,</l>
                  <l>Yea, euen of <hi>Edwards-</hi>selfe, except amongst them he should liue,</l>
                  <l>Too well experienced what law by Proxie Princes giue.</l>
                  <l>Much therefore did in action, more in murmor hence proceed,</l>
                  <l>Till by this Policie the King did thus his purpose speed.</l>
                  <l>* In <hi>Wales</hi> he at <hi>Carnaruon</hi> with his Queene the Winter pas,</l>
                  <l>Where <hi>Edward</hi> his first-borne, surnam'd <hi>Carnaruō, Welsh-</hi>borne was:</l>
                  <l>The King, conuening then the <hi>Welsh,</hi> made promise he would name</l>
                  <l>Vnto their Nation such a Prince as none for ought could blame,</l>
                  <l>Borne in their Countrie, and could not one word in <hi>English</hi> say,</l>
                  <l>Whō gladly, on those Termes, the Lords of <hi>Wales</hi> swore to obey:</l>
                  <l>* The King thē nam'd his Infant-Sonne, and progrest thēce away.</l>
                  <l>Hence <hi>Englands</hi> Heires-apparant haue of <hi>Wales</hi> bin Princes, till</l>
                  <l>Our Queene deceast conceald her Heire, I wot not for what skill.</l>
                  <l>But now may <hi>Cambries</hi> frollike, for though vertuous many since,</l>
                  <l>Yet parallel at least the best may their now hopefull Prince:</l>
                  <l>And theirs is hapt the honour that <hi>Brutes</hi> triple Diuident</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Locrin, Camber, Albanack,</hi> reuerteth whence it went:</l>
                  <l>For Home-againe to <hi>Britons</hi> is intired <hi>Britaine</hi> sent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So inaccessible is <hi>Wales,</hi> so mountanous, and craggie,</l>
                  <l>That to refresh my Muse, as els occasioned, Here lagge I,</l>
                  <l>Only that to <hi>Elizabeth</hi> hath Office tithed bragge I.</l>
                  <l>Was neuer Prince affoorded Muse a sweeter subiect then</l>
                  <pb n="416" facs="tcp:20257:41"/>
                  <l> Her life and Raigne, or Age thereto that apted choicer men.</l>
                  <l>Yet, as if <hi>Perseus</hi> mounted on his <hi>Pegasus</hi> held out</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Gorgons</hi> head, stone▪ still stand all should go that Taske about.</l>
                  <l>O that would He might it commaund it recommend vnto</l>
                  <l>Some Artist, worthie such a worke of Raritie to do!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Moses</hi> the Patriarkes, <hi>Caesar</hi> did himselfe and others sing,</l>
                  <l>Stoore like <hi>heroick</hi> Pennes, and She were pen-worke for a King.</l>
                  <l>Should then, liefe Lord, your royall-selfe vouchsafe an Ouer-view</l>
                  <l>Of whomsoeuer arting it, to giue it <hi>Species</hi> true,</l>
                  <l>Long after my decease may like (liu'd like) doe like for you:</l>
                  <l>But howsoeuer, happely Liue, Raigne, your Foes subdue.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20257:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>